<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A discovery of peace: or, The thoughts of the Almighty for the ending of his peoples calamities. Intimated in a sermon at Christ-church London, before the Right Honourable, the Lord Mayor, the right worshipfull the Aldermen; together with the worshipfull companies of the said city, upon the 24th of April, 1644. Being the solemn day of their publike Humiliation and monethly fast. By John Strickland, B.D. pastor of the church at St. Edmunds, in the city of New Sarum; a member of the Assembly of Divines.</title>
            <author>Strickland, John, 1600 or 1601-1670.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1644</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 120 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 27 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A94047</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S5969</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E48_5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R14414</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99859661</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99859661</idno>
            <idno type="VID">111756</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A94047)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 111756)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 9:E48[5])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A discovery of peace: or, The thoughts of the Almighty for the ending of his peoples calamities. Intimated in a sermon at Christ-church London, before the Right Honourable, the Lord Mayor, the right worshipfull the Aldermen; together with the worshipfull companies of the said city, upon the 24th of April, 1644. Being the solemn day of their publike Humiliation and monethly fast. By John Strickland, B.D. pastor of the church at St. Edmunds, in the city of New Sarum; a member of the Assembly of Divines.</title>
                  <author>Strickland, John, 1600 or 1601-1670.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 39, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by M. Simmons for Henry Overton, and are to be sold at his shop entring into Popes-head Alley, out of Lumbard-street,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1644.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Jeremiah XXIX, 11 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Fast-day sermons --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:111756:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A DISCOVERY OF PEACE: OR, The thoughts of the ALMIGHTY For the ending of his Peoples CALAMITIES.</p>
            <p>Intimated in a <hi>Sermon</hi> at Chriſt-Church <hi>London,</hi> before the Right Honourable, the Lord Mayor, the Right worſhipfull the Aldermen; together with the worſhipfull Companies of the ſaid City, upon the 24<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>April,</hi> 1644.</p>
            <p>Being the ſolemn day of their publike Humiliation and monethly Faſt.</p>
            <p>By JOHN STRICKLAND, <hi>B. D.</hi> Paſtor of the Church at S<hi rend="sup">t.</hi> 
               <hi>Edmunds,</hi> in the City of <hi>New Sarum;</hi> A Member of the Aſſembly of Divines.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Iſaiah 27. Verſ. 5.</hi>
               </bibl> Let him take hold of my ſtrength, that hee may mak peace with me, <hi>and</hi> he ſhall make peace with me.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>M. Simmons</hi> for <hi>Henry Overton</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop entring into <hi>Popes-head Alley,</hi> out of <hi>Lumbard-ſtreet,</hi> 1644.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:111756:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:111756:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOURABLE, Iohn VVollaſton, Lord Mayor of the famous City of <hi>LONDON,</hi> Together with the Right Worſhipfull the ALDERMEN his Brethren.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honorable and Worſhipfull,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S it was your requeſt, that occaſioned me to offer theſe my Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditations to your ears in the Pulpit: So is it nothing elſe that brings them forth (ſuch as they are) from the Preſſe to bee thus preſented to your
<pb facs="tcp:111756:3"/>view, and under your names, that ſo they might have a paſſe into the world: they have been already in your eares, they are now before your eyes, the Lord write them in all our hearts, that we may be do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of the word, and not hearers onely, leſt we deceive our own ſelves! When I ſtood upon my watch to ſee what the Lord would ſay unto mee, that I might ſpeak unto you, he directed me to make this <hi>Diſcovery of Peace</hi> before you, when you ſate in the duſt before him, humbling your ſoules, and crying migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily unto God, to turn from his fierce an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger that we periſh not: and indeed God is never more ready to give out himſelfe, and to communicate his <hi>thoughts</hi> unto men in a ſpirituall way, then at ſuch a time; nor is the ſoule ſo capable of divine <hi>Diſcoveries</hi> from God at any time, as when it is in ſuch a poſture of humiliati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: which gives me hope that God inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb facs="tcp:111756:3"/>to ſend home into your hearts ſome light and influence from this truth, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage and keep up your ſpirits againſt all the oppoſition which you finde in the cauſe of God and the Kingdome, and to maintaine your zeale and forwardneſſe therein, for which your ever-to-be-re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned Citie is now ſo much and ſo juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly honored. For though the viſion be yet for an appointed time, &amp; in the mean time the ſword devoureth on the right hand &amp; on the left, yet we may wel wait for it, becauſe it will ſurely come, and will not tarry, and when it commeth it will bee a tree of life. Now that God hath revea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led unto you his gracious <hi>thoughts for the ending of his peoples calamities,</hi> (even ſuch as you could <hi>expect</hi>) he look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ethth at you ſhould do ſomwhat for the furtherance thereof, that may be worthy of your place and eminencie whereunto the Lord hath advanced you: To help
<pb facs="tcp:111756:4"/>forward <hi>an expected end</hi> is a work wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy the hand of a Prince. <hi>Numa</hi> built a Temple,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> he dedicated to Faith and Peace, becauſe hee deſired that they might dwell together under one roof: the worke that I lay before you, (honoured Gentlemen) is altogether as honorable as <hi>Numa's:</hi> I need not now ſhew you how to doe it, you are partly directed in the Sermon, but you have given the world ful proof that you know how to doe it, in that you have done it, and do it at this day, ſo effectually with your Armies, with your Eſtates, with your prayers, everie way: Goe on and doe ſtill like the Citizens of <hi>London:</hi> and if God bleſſe your endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours, wee may yet hope to ſee what <hi>Nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma</hi> never ſaw, <hi>Truth and Peace dwell together under one roofe in this Kingdome.</hi> Be pleaſed yet to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain a word or two, to expedite your willing endevours in bringing <hi>our
<pb facs="tcp:111756:4"/>Churches calamities to an expected end:</hi> you know there are a generation of Ambo-dexters among us, that do pretend to ſeek the ſame God, &amp; to build in the work of the Lord with us, as the Iewes adverſaries did in the building of the Temple, <hi>Ezra 4.2.</hi> But as <hi>Zerubbabel</hi> and the chiefe of the Fathers were aware of them then: ſo our <hi>Zerubbabels</hi> (I hope) and you the chiefe of our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, are alſo aware of theſe now: Are they not even ſuch as the Pſalmiſt deſcribes? <hi>They put forth their hands againſt ſuch as be at peace with them, they break their covenant; the words of their mouth are ſmoother then butter, but warre is in their hearts; their words are ſofter then oyle, yet are they drawn ſwords?</hi> Pſa <hi>55.20.21.</hi> Their words are peace, peace, <hi>&amp; pacem poſcimus omnes,</hi> but they love not truth and peace, they broak for treaties of peace, under which they wold now betray us. For in truth their deſigne is to hinder your endevours in bringing on this <hi>expected end:</hi> it will not be unneceſſary that you have an eye upon them. Next, let me prevaile with you to bee tender of Gods honour, in what peculiarly belongs unto him, as you expect God ſhould be tender of us in bringing the <hi>Calamities</hi> of our Church unto this deſirable <hi>end.</hi> Our Worthies in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament have piouſly provided for the ſanctifying of our Chriſtian Sabbath, improve your Authorities for the exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting of ſuch wholſom laws, ſo much concerning the Lord our God, eſpecially reforme, I beſeech you, all Exchange-meetings
<pb facs="tcp:111756:5"/>that day, unleſſe you could be ſure that men would come thither with a deſire of no other news then what they might heare from heaven that day: if any thing, ſurely this is a blemiſh, &amp; that in the face of your beautiſul Citie; you have worthily cleared your ſtreets of the notorious oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions of Idolatry, let not anyplace be left (eſpecially ſuch a publick place) in the midſt of you, an occaſion of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneneſſe. And go on, as I hear you have piouſly reſolved, to take inn God more ſolemnly, into your publick conſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, then formerly, by beginning and ending ſuch your meetings,<note place="margin">A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="6 letters">
                     <desc>••••••</desc>
                  </gap>us N. A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>. l. <hi>7.</hi> c. <hi>10</hi>
               </note> with prayer, like <hi>Pub. Scipio</hi> a famous Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man (of whom it was ſaid, <hi>Ejus vita erat diis dedita</hi>) who was wont to go to the Capitoll before he went to the Senat, to his prayers before his publick buſineſſe. And I doubt not but the Lord will continue to protect and honour this your famous Citie, in delighting to uſe it as a choyce and eminent inſtrument in his hand, to bring the preſent and preſsing calamities of our dear countrey, to an <hi>expected end,</hi> and to continue you in a peaceable and quiet habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation. For which purpoſe I commend this whole Citie, together w<hi rend="sup">th</hi> your government, Counſels, perſons and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments to the bleſsing and care of the moſt high God. And this ſhall be the prayer of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your willing ſervant in the Goſpel of Chriſt, IOHN STRICKLAND.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:111756:5"/>
            <head>A Diſcovery of PEACE, or the thoughts of the Almighty for the ending of his peoples Calamities.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>JEREM. 29.11.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>For I know the thoughts that I think towards you, ſaith the Lord, thoughts of peace, and not of evill, to give you an expected end.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Jewiſh Church was now in a ſad conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>od was provoked againſt her for the ſins of K. <hi>Manaſſeh,</hi> eſpecially for that innocent blood which he ſhed, and with which he fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Jeruſalem; and for which the Lord pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſted he would not be pacified,<note place="margin">2 King 24 3.4.</note> 2 <hi>King.</hi> 24.3, 4. therefore <hi>Jehoiachim,</hi> with the greateſt part of the Iewes, were now carried away captive into Babylon, there to remain in ſlaverie for threeſcore and ten yeares: And now becauſe the people could not beare the thoughts of ſo long a bondage, there aroſe up among them falſe prophets (which are alwayes ready to feed the peoples humors) &amp; put them in hope that their ſlavery ſhould be of a far ſhorter conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance, and that they ſhould very ſuddenly returne into their own Land again; namely, that they ſhould not continue in bondage a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove two yeares, as you have it, <hi>Jerem.</hi> 28.3, 4.<note place="margin">Jer. 28.3, 4.</note> To prevent the miſchief that this doctrine might bring upon the people (name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the peoples impenitencie and carnall ſecuritie, by being miſ-led into ſuch deceitfull expectations) the Prophet <hi>Jeremie</hi> writes a let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter from <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> unto the people of the captivitie, in this chapter; and therein, to undeceive the people, hee adviſeth them that they
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:111756:6"/>ſhould (for all that the falſe Prophets had ſaid) make proviſion for a longer ſtay in <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> then for two years, that they ſhould marry wives, and build houſes, and plant Orchards; he preſſeth on them that counſell from the 4. verſe of this Chapter,<note place="margin">Verſe 4-15.</note> unto the 15.</p>
            <p>Next, foraſmuch as he ſaw their hearts hancred after <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> that they might return to their own Land again, he acquaints them in the ſecond place, that the remnant of the people, that were not yet carried away from <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> ſhould be very ſhortly led into a like captivity, and the Citie of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> (on which their eye was fixed ſo much) turned into a ſhes and deſtroyed; ſo that their hopes in that particular were daſhed. This argument he preſſeth on them from the 15, verſe to 20. So you ſhall find it in the Hiſtorie, 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 25.<note place="margin">Verſ. 15-20. 2 Kings 25.</note> In the former branch of the Prophets Letter, (wherein he doth indevour to take up the peoples thoughts about longer ſtay in Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon) be pleaſed to mark two conſiderable things, that are diſtinct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly delivered.</p>
            <p>Firſt, he laboureth to confute the error of thoſe falſe prophets, that told them they ſhould ſtay no longer in Babylon then two yeares, and he lets them know that theſe are but dreames of their own, they had no ſuch warrant for any thing from the word of God;<note place="margin">Verſ. 8.9.</note> this at the 8. and 9. verſe, whereby hee bridles their confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, that they ſhould not bee too haſty in expectation of their return ſo ſuddenly.</p>
            <p>Secondly, leſt they ſhould caſt off all hope and confidence of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance, in the next place he labours to maintaine their hope, and ſtrengthen their faith to wait on God: for though hee would not bring deliverance in ſuch a time as the falſe prophets had foretold, (in the compaſſe of two yeares) yet hee would not faile to bring them deliverance in due time; he would deliver them, but not then; he would deliver them, but he would take his owne time for it: And in the mean time God would not forget their captivity, and his thoughts concerning them, were thoughts of peace, as in the words of my Text. <hi>For I know my thoughts that I think towards you, ſaith the Lord, thoughts of peace, and not of evill, to give you an expected end,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Before I come to the words of the Text, give me leave a little to inſiſt upon the deſigne and ſcope of the holy Ghoſt in this letter of the Prophet <hi>Jeremie;</hi> wherein, as he did intend to check them in their groundleſſe expectations of a ſudden deliverance, ſo he labors
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:111756:6"/>to bring them to, and ſupport them in a patient waiting on God for deliverance in his own time. The point from hence is this.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctrine. </seg>
               </label> That God would have his people in the times of their trouble, calmly to wait on him, and to be neither too haſty, nor hopeleſſe, concerning their return from captivitie.</p>
            <p>You may obſerve that the Prophet <hi>Habakkuk</hi> (who is conceived to be contemporary with the Prophet <hi>Jeremie,</hi> and therefore to ſpeak of the ſame thing) gives the very ſame advice or command concerning this very buſines of the Babyloniſh captivity. <hi>The viſion,</hi> ſaith he in 2. <hi>Hab.</hi> 3, 4. <hi>is yet for an appointed time,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hab. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.3, 4.</note> 
               <hi>but at the end it ſhall ſpeak and not lie, though it tarry, wait for it: for it ſhal come, and it ſhall not tarry. Behold his ſoul which is lifted up, is not upright in him.</hi> Mark, he would have men to be of that frame and temper of heart, that they ſhould patiently and calmly poſſeſſe their ſoules in waiting on God, though the viſion for their deliverance be ſomewhat long, and it be not yet come. It is the obſervation of Mr. <hi>Calvin,</hi> that the Prophet in commanding a waiting temper of ſpirit,<note place="margin">Coarguit fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vorem immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicum qui nos abripit. <hi>Calv. in locum.</hi>
               </note> checks that common haſtineſſe, or hotneſſe of ſpirit, wherin men are too much carried away with longing after deliverance, and therefore he would have men to poſſeſſe themſelves with more patience: For he ſaith, <hi>Though deliverance tarry, it ſhall not tarry.</hi> It may tarry in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of our deſires, <hi>Etiam celeritas in deſiderio mora eſt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Paraeus.</note> Let deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance be never ſo ſwift, it cannot come ſo ſoon as it is looked for, mens hearts are ſo up in expectations of bleſſings in that kind; but it ſhall not tarry in reſpect of Gods own determination, <hi>Qui in ipſa tarditate ſemperaccelerat,</hi> it ſhall never ſtay beyond his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell and appointment. His ſoule that is lifted up in pride of heart therfore, and cannot humbly ſubmit unto the Lords pleaſure, but in ſtead of waiting upon God, will ſeek a Tower of refuge elſewhere, and impatiently withdraw his heart, or draw back, as the Apoſtle renders the word, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.38. his ſoul is not upright in him.<note place="margin">Heb. 10.38.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſons. </seg>1</label> Firſt, it is Gods prerogative Royal to lay on and to take off af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction, and that in his own time, he hath the diſpoſall of the ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and opportunitie of both, he challengeth it in 32. <hi>Deut.</hi> 39. <hi>See now, that I, even I am be, and there is no God with me; I kill,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 32.39.</note> 
               <hi>and I make alive; I wound, and I heal: neither is there any that can deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver out of my hand.</hi> It is as it were a thing hereditarie to the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head, if as I may ſo ſay, a thing peculiar to him, to lay on, and to take off afflictions at his own appointment; Hee it is that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:111756:7"/>deliverance, and therefore it is hee alone that we ſhould a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe all our deliverance to, and upon whom we ſhould wait for all our deliverance. It is reported of <hi>Domitian,</hi> that when he eſcaped from <hi>Vitellius</hi> ſeeking to deſtroy him, he reſolved that in the place where he lay hid, he would build a Temple, and he would dedicate it <hi>Jovi Cuſtodi, ſeque in ſinu Dei ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cravit,</hi> ſaith the Hiſtorian.<note place="margin">Tacitus.</note> And had a heathen ſo much zeale for the honour of an Idoll-god, that hee would aſcribe it all to him? How much more ſhould we aſcribe the honour of our deliverances to the true God, and write upon our Temples and monuments of praiſe, not <hi>Jovi,</hi> but <hi>Deo cuſtodi,</hi> to our God our great deliverer.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, a diligent and patient waiting on God in the day of trouble, is the ſafeſt way we can take; let men try all other wayes, and they ſhall find this is the only way: for he is both able to help, and he is alſo of a good diſpoſition, (if I may ſay ſo little of him.) The Apoſtle on that ground exhorts men, to caſt all their burthen on him,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 5.6, 7.</note> in 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.6, 7. <hi>Caſt all your care on him, for hee careth for you;</hi> he taketh to heart your condition, hee is ſenſible of all your miſery. For a man to goe any other way, it will be in vain, it will adde to his miſery, rather then deliver him. You have an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent and a cleare example in <hi>Ephraim, Hoſea</hi> 5.13, 14. <hi>When E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraim ſaw his ſickneſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hoſ. 5.13, 14.</note> 
               <hi>and Judah ſaw his wound, Ephraim</hi> tooke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother courſe then this in the Doctrine, hee did not wait on God, but <hi>he went to King Jareb, yet could not he help you, nor cure you of your wound.</hi> And whereas before the Lord had been but unto them as a moth, and as rottenneſſe, in his judgements, now he was reſolved to become as a Lion, he would teare them, and there ſhould none be able to deliver them,<note place="margin">Verſ. 14.</note> 
               <hi>verſ.</hi> 14. And (which is moſt of all conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable to the point) <hi>Ephraim</hi> that went another way, was faine to return to God at laſt, and ſeek help from him. <hi>Come, let us returne to the Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hoſea 6.1.</note> 
               <hi>for he hath torn, and he will heal us; he hath ſmitten, and hee will bind us up.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>1</label> Firſt, it may ſerve to humble and to lay us low before the Lord this day, that ſince God requireth ſuch a calme, a patient, ſuch a waiting frame of heart in his people upon him, in the day of their trouble, our hearts ſhould be ſo farre (as we know they are) from this waiting frame, that we ſhould be ſo much diſtempered as wee are with pettiſhneſſe, and with impatience under the hand of God; ſubmiſſion is that, my brethren, which God eſpecially looks for at
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:111756:7"/>our hands, whereby he might have occaſion given to deliver us.<note place="margin">Levit. 26.40, 41, 42.</note> 26. <hi>Levit.</hi> 40, 41, 42. <hi>verſe,</hi> when the people of <hi>Iſrael</hi> were in their affliction, <hi>If then their uncircumciſed hearts bee humbled, and they then accept of the puniſhment of their iniquities, then will I remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber my covenant with Jacob, and alſo my covenant with Iſaac, and alſo my covenant with Abraham will I remember, and I will remember the Land.</hi> Mark! If when we have walked contrary to God, and wee find that God hath walked contrary to us, as at the 40. <hi>verſe,</hi> if then we will accept of our puniſhment, that is to ſay, if we will kindly take it, humbly ſubmit to it, patiently goe under it; then with God remember his covenant, then will God remember our Land, then will God be favourable to us. It much concerneth us to bee hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, and aſhamed this day, that there is ſuch a frame of heart with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in us, ſo farre diſcordant and unſuteable to theſe times of calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie that are now on us. Alas, my brethren, wee are rather deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratly ſick of <hi>Davids</hi> diſeaſe, ſometimes we are too high, ſometimes we are too low; he was ſo ſet on the top of his ſtrong mountaine, as if he ſhould never be removed, and ſo are we. And ſometimes he was too low, ſo dejected that he concluded it was ion vain that ever he ſerved God, that ever hee looked for any hope from God, that ever he waited on God, as he complained in the 73. <hi>Pſalm.,</hi> 13, 14. So is it with us, my brethren,<note place="margin">Pſal. 73.13, 14.</note> we reel to and fro in our paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, from one extream to another, as if ſo be we were drunk with impatiencie and with preſumption by turnes. Beloved, how ſhould this affect us, and make us aſhamed, while we look up in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of God this day,<note place="margin">Evils of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiencie in trouble.</note> to think that we are of ſuch a diſtempered frame of heart? The better to move us to be humble and aſhamed for it, conſider what inconveniences follow hereon.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, by this means it commeth to paſſe, that wee loſe all our ſweet comfort and Soul-ſupporting peace, that otherwiſe wee might have in the midſt of our troubles, as the Church had found in her experience, and therefore ſets it down in her ſong of praiſe, to encourage the Church to wait on God in after times, 26 <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 3, 4. <hi>Thou wilt keep him in perfect peace whoſe mind is ſtaied on thee,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſai. 26.3, 4.</note> 
               <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he truſteth ion thee. Truſt in the Lord for ever, for in the Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hovah is eve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>laſting ſtrength.</hi> God himſelfe, who is the God of peace, will undertake to keep thoſe in perfect peace, or (as the word im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports by the repetition of it, peace, peace) in peace aſſuredly, whoſe minds are ſtaid on him, as <hi>Junius, cogitationi in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>itenti;</hi> whom our laſt
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:111756:8"/>tranſlation followes; and though <hi>Calvin</hi> renders the words a little differently, <hi>cogitatio fixa,</hi> as relating unto Gods counſels, which are fixedly ſet from everlaſting to give peace unto his Church,<note place="margin">Non apponitur nota dativica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s; expend at lectores annon magu conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at referre ad Deum, C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lvin on Iſai. <hi>26.</hi>
               </note> (of which reading he gives an * account, and wherein hee leaves the reader free to his own judgenent) yet both <hi>Junius</hi> and <hi>Calvin</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, that God will not faile to give his Church and people peace, that patiently wait upon him, peace with God, which is of all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the moſt perfect and fundamentall peace; peace in their owne ſoules in the middeſt of their troubles and diſtreſſes; and this, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their truſting in him, ſhall be a continuall peace, ſeeing their God is of an<note n="*" place="margin">Rupes ſaecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorum.</note> everlaſting power and ſtrength to defend and keep it for them: But through this want of truſt in God, it is that we are ſo unſetled in theſe times of trouble, that we are ſometimes car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried too high by carnall confidence, into provoking preſumption; and ſometimes caſt downe too low by carnall feares into dejection of ſpirit. The beleeving heart of the righteous, ſhall be brought into a more excellent frame, as is promiſed, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 112.7. <hi>Hee ſhall not be afraid of evill tidings,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 112.6.</note> 
               <hi>his heart is fixed, truſting in the Lord;</hi> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther good nor bad newes ſhal move it inordinatly: he ſhall be in the midſt of all ſtormes, like a Ship that lies ſafe at Anker in a good Haven; whereas a man that is without faith in God, is even as a Ship on the waves without Rudder, and without Anker, either to guide, or ſtay her; ſhe is toſſed ſometimes up, and ſometimes down, and carried ſometimes forward, ſometimes backward, ſometimes as high as heaven, and ſometimes almoſt as long as hell. So that his ſoule,<note place="margin">Pſal. 107. 27, 27.</note> like their ſoules, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 107.26, 27. reeles and melts in him becauſe of the trouble. A diſquieted and impatient temper of heart in trouble, brings the loſſe of all the comfort, peace, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment of God, that a man might otherwiſe have even in the midſt of trouble.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, by this means it ſhall come to paſſe, that a man ſhall, queſtion at leaſt, if not utterly deny Gods power and providence; and ſo God himſelfe, if he dare not wait and patiently truſt upon the Lord ion the time of trouble: he queſtions whether there be ſuch wiſedome, and goodneſſe, and faithfulneſſe, and power in God, as may warrant ſuch a truſt, which is no other but to queſtion whether God be God or no: the Prophet puts it all upon a meek and patient waiting on God,<note place="margin">Pſal. 46.10.</note> 46. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 10. <hi>Be ſtill, and know that I am God.</hi> As if he ſhould ſay, If you will acknowledge me to be God, then wait
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:111756:8"/>on me, and that quietly and be you not tranſported with this or that paſſion: He chargeh it on them there eſpecially, becauſe they had ſeen ſo much of God as they had, verſe 8, 9.<note place="margin">Verſ. 8.9.</note> 
               <hi>Come ſee the workes of the Lord, what</hi> deſtruction and <hi>deſolation he hath made in the earth,</hi> I have deſtroyed your enemies, and laid waſt Countries for your ſakes, and now therefore be quiet, wait on the Lord, and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge that I am God. So if we ſhould be ſpoken to, to ſee what God hath done, and how he hath delivered us of late, and what deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations he hath made among the enemies: And if after all this, we cannot yet wait on the Lord and be ſtill, we acknowledge not Gods power to have done it. Nay, if we cannot wait on the Lord in a holy dependance for the Churches deliverance in due time, we ſhall in effect ſay little leſſe of God, then the Prince did at the ſiege of <hi>Samaria,</hi> when the Prophet foretold that a great plenty ſhould ſucceed the famine,<note place="margin">2 King. 7.19.</note> 2 <hi>King.</hi> 7.19. <hi>If God ſhould make windows in heaven, might ſuch a thing be?</hi> The thing is even impoſſible: And if we ſhould ſpeak ſo like an Infidell of the Lord, we might juſtly look to be puniſhed like him. God ſent a plenty in <hi>Samaria,</hi> but he did not eate of it: So God may ſend his Church deliverance, and we, with ours, be juſtly deprived of any comfort therein.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> A third evill that followeth on this impatiencie and fretting of ſpirit under the hand of God, is, that it leadeth to Apoſtaſie, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by a man ſhall utterly fall from God and his cauſe, then to bethink all the coſt and charges, and all the diſquietment and bodily labour that befalleth men at ſuch a time as this, is the way to take off the heart, and to ſeek out ſome other way,<note place="margin">Hab. 2.3, 4.</note> as is intimated <hi>Hab.</hi> 2.3, 4. the Prophet ſaith, <hi>If any mans heart be lifted up in him,</hi> ſignifying that if any man will goe to any other Tower or Sanctuary beſide the Lord. The Apoſtle he renders it, <hi>a withdrawing his heart from the Lord, and he ſhall have no pleaſure in him, Heb.</hi> 10.38, 39.<note place="margin">Heb. 1038.39.</note> So that ſuch as have once loſt their patience, and cannot beare thoſe trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles that befall the Church, will fall from leſſe to more, and will become at length an Apoſtates. And alas, are we without experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence this day, of the ſad fruits of diſcontent? How many hath it brought to an utter forſaking of Gods cauſe, and his truth? Like the Smith in the time of King <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixt;<note place="margin">Fox in Acts and Mon.</note> that ſometimes had been very forward in matters of Religion, and had been a hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py inſtrument, as it ſhould ſeem, for the converſion of a young man, and ſetting him forward in the wayes and profeſſion of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:111756:9"/>ſo farre that at length the young man was taken hold of, and impriſoned for the Goſpels ſake: this young man in priſon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinking and remembring his old friend that had been ſo good to him, to whom he alwayes carried a reverent reſpect, he laid out to know whether or not this Smith that had been an inſtrument of ſo much good to him, was no taken hold of, and laid in priſon as himſelfe; but finding he was not, he took occaſion to expoſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late with him, and ſo to feele his diſpoſition, and to know whether he did think it comfortable for him to continue in priſon, and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he would incourage him to burn at the ſtake for religion. He returneth this anſwer to him, ſaith he, your cauſe is good, and you doe well to ſuffer for it. But for my part, I cannot bring my heart to burn for Religion. But it ſeemeth by the event, that he that could not burn for Religion, he did burn for his Apoſtaſie: For within a little time after, he that could not burne for Religion, had his ſhop and his houſe on fire, and was burnt in the midſt of it. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved, I produce it to this end, that we may ſee when men cannot bring their hearts patiently and meekly to ſubmit to the ſuffering of what God ſhall lay upon his Church for the teſtimony of the Goſpel, it is too too likely they will fall to flat Apoſtaſie, and utterly turn from the Lord, and then he will ſurely meet with them: ſo that firſt or laſt they ſhall not eſcape.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly and laſtly, another evill of this impatiencie and fret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe of ſpirit under the ſufferings of the Goſpel, brings us to murmuring, a provoking condition in the eyes of the Almighty, 1 Cor. 10.10. we have an example.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>2</label> The ſecond uſe of the point is, That ſeeing God lookes that his people ſhould ſo patiently wait on him in the time of trouble, and neither be too haſty nor hopeleſſe, it ſhould ſtirre us up to ſtrive to be at leaſt content, if not very willing, to lie ſtill under our affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, though they be heavie, even as long as the wiſe God of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and earth ſhall pleaſe; we ſhould be willing to let God doe as he will, let him afflict us, and correct us as long as ſeems him good; we will not limit the holy One of Iſrael: wee ſhould labour for <hi>Luthers</hi> ſpirit,<note place="margin">Luther.</note> 
               <hi>Mallem ruere cum Chriſto, quam regnare cum Caeſare,</hi> I had rather I were ruined with Chriſt, then that I ſhould reigne as a King without him; wee ſhould labour to bee of that ſpirit, that though we ſuffer never ſo much, yet having the cauſe of Chriſt, and partaking of the ſufferings of Chriſt, is better then all the jollitie
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:111756:9"/>and ſecuritie we can have without him, and therefore <hi>Moſes</hi> was of that Heroick ſpirit, he would <hi>rather chuſe to ſuffer affliction with the people of God, then to enjoy the pleaſures of ſinne for a ſeaſon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 11.25.</note> 11. <hi>Heb.</hi> 25. And, beloved, me thinkes we ſhould learn to make a vertue of neceſſity; there is a fatall neceſſity of ſuffering on the one hand, or the other, with or againſt Chriſt. I may then expoſtulate with you, as <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> ſometime did excellently with ſome others, <hi>Seeing we muſt all ſuffer, &amp; ſeeing we muſt bear afflictions, why do we not rather chuſe to ſuffer for the Goſpels ſake, that brings with it ſo many Crownes and Lawrels,</hi> ſo many comforts and conſolations above all other ſufferings in the world? You ſee then that this patience in ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring for the Goſpels ſake, is a very needfull grace: So the Apoſtle, <hi>We have need of patience, that when we have done the will of God, we may enjoy the promiſes,</hi> 10. <hi>Heb.</hi> 36.<note place="margin">Heb. 10.36.</note> I might here relate unto you the grave counſell of <hi>Judith;</hi> and though the Hiſtorie be Apocryphall, I am ſure the counſell is Canonicall, the counſell, I ſay, which <hi>Judith</hi> gave to the men of <hi>Bethulia,</hi> in <hi>Judith</hi> 8.14, 15, 16. <hi>verſes,</hi> when the men of <hi>Bethulia</hi> being beſieged by the enemy, had taken up a raſh reſolution, that if God did not come and deliver them within 5 dayes, they would deliver up the Citie to the enemy that lay be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them; <hi>Judith</hi> gravely thus beſpeakes them, <hi>Nay, my brethren, let us not provoke the Lord our God to anger: for if hee come not within five dayes, he is able to defend us when he will, even every day, or to deſtroy us before our enemies, therefore let us wait for ſalvation of him, and call upon him, and he will heare us if it pleaſe him.</hi> So may I ſay to you all this day, Farre be it from us, that we ſhould yeeld up the cauſe, and all we have, if God ſhould not at ſuch a time, or ſuch a time, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver us; let us not ſpeak ſo to provoke the Lord: Let us wait on the Lord, and call upon him, and he will help us, if it pleaſe him.</p>
            <p>To ſtirre up our hearts thus meekly and cheerfully to ſubmit to the diſpoſall of Gods hand in our ſufferings.<note place="margin">Motives</note>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Three things may be propoſed to you by way of motive.</p>
            <p>Firſt conſider, though God afflict us never ſo much, yet be well perſwaded and aſſured, he will not lay on afflictions more on us then needs muſt. If Gods people be in a ſad condition, or a ſorrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full eſtate, it is <hi>but if need be we are in heavineſſe,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.6.<note place="margin">1. Pet. 1.6.</note> God doth never afflict his people meerly out of ſoveraignty, becauſe he will doe it; that is farre from him, 3. <hi>Lament.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lam. 3.33.</note> I doe not tread upon men, ſayes God, as if I would cruſh them, or ſhew my power over
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:111756:10"/>them; no, that is farre from God. <hi>For he doth not afflict willingly, nor grieve the children of men, to cruſh under his feet the priſoners of the earth.</hi> But when he afflicts his people the moſt ſeverely, he doth it as a Refiner, as a Goldſmith doth put his metall into the fire, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he would ſeparate the droſſe from it, and purifie it; ſo God puts his people in the fire of affliction, with ſome purpoſe or other, for their benefit and advantage. The Phyſician, though after long evacuations and purgings, he continue the ſame courſe, and bring the Patient yet lower, it is ſtill with a purpoſe to take away the peccant humour, and to cleanſe him. So God in afflicting his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, 27. <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 9. <hi>By this ſhall the iniquitie of Jacob be purged, and this is all the fruit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſai. 27.9.</note> 
               <hi>the taking away of his ſinne.</hi> God will not lay one af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction on his people more, nor continue it an houre longer then he knoweth it needfull.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, the ſuffering of affliction for the cauſe of Chriſt, is very honorable, and therefore we need not ſo fret, nor be ſo impatient under them, they are honorable wounds we ſuffer for Chriſt, which maketh the people of God beautifull in the eyes of all good men. You may obſerve the Lord reſerves it as a ſingular priviledge in the 1. <hi>Phil.</hi> 29.<note place="margin">Phil. 1.29.</note> 
               <hi>To you it is given not onely to beleeve, but alſo to ſuffer for the name of Chriſt.</hi> And the Apoſtles tooke it for a dignity that they might ſuffer for the name of God, rejoycing <hi>that they were accounted worthy to ſuffer for his Name,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 5.41.</note> 5. <hi>Acts</hi> 41. And therefore the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Martyrs <hi>ſuffered the ſpoyling of their goods with joy,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 10.34.</note> 
               <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.34. We doe it with fretting and murmuring, and that muſt be taken from us which we ſhould contribute unto the cauſe of God, wee count it our puniſhment, they counted it their crown and glory. It is reported of <hi>Hooper,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Fox his Acts and Monum.</note> that when hee was Biſhop of Worceſter, his Armes were <hi>a Lamb in a flaming buſh, incircled with the rayes of the Sun beams,</hi> not under the notion of an <hi>Agnus Dei.</hi> But if it was, as it is obſerved by thoſe that read the ſtory, under another intimation, &amp; thus we may undertake to emblazon them. The Lamb ſignifieth an innocent Chriſtian, and the burning buſh the fire of perſecution; and the Sunne beames the beautie and glory of the innocent Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian in thoſe ſufferings.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, conſider well the priviledge of ſuffering for Chriſt; It is no ſmall advantage for a Chriſtian, it being the way to perfect the graces of God that are in him: you may ſee as much 1. <hi>James</hi> 2, 3.<note place="margin">James 1.2.3.</note> 
               <hi>Count it all joy when you fall into divers temptations, knowing that
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:111756:10"/>the triall of your faith worketh patience, that yee may be perfect.</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed it is a childs portion, a thing that God will give to all his own children; and therefore the Apoſtle argueth, that God deals with his people like children, when they ſuffer for him, 12. <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.<note place="margin">Heb. 12.7. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>If you indure chaſtening, God dealeth with you as ſons.</hi> If you ſuffer with pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, ſaith the originall: But if you ſuffer frettingly, or with im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patience, that is not the ſigne of a child, nor the badge of a ſufferer for God. The ſufferings that are laid on his people by the hand of God, they are not grievous meerly becauſe they are ſufferings,<note place="margin">Non ſunt om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus oneroſa tolerantibus, ſed tol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rare nolen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ib<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n. <hi>Salvian.</hi>
               </note> but becauſe of mens impatience they become grievous. This hath been ſpoken by way of encouragement, to lay downe our ſelves pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently and meekly under the hand of God in the time of tribulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and to beare the ſufferings that God ſhall lay on his Church.</p>
            <p>Let me next point at the meanes how we may bring our hearts into ſuch a frame, that we may with meekneſſe and calmneſſe of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, under goe the hand of God, he layes on us, how heavie ſoever it may ſeem at preſent. There are three directions.<note place="margin">Directions.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, let a man conſider and look into the juſtneſſe of the hand of God on his people, on us. If there be any thing thou canſt chalenge God of injuſtice for, then thou haſt leave to fret and to bee impati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent; but when all that God brings on thee, or on the Nation, or on the Church, is moſt juſt: ſo that God is righteous in all that hee brings on us, there is no place for impatiencie. <hi>Why doth the living man complain,</hi> ſaith the Prophet, <hi>a man for the puniſhment of his ſins?</hi> 3. Lam. 39. As if he ſhould ſay,<note place="margin">Lam. 3.39.</note> It is right that a man ſhould ſuffer for <hi>his ſinne.</hi> With this it is that the Church ſtops her own mouth in 7. <hi>Micah</hi> 9. <hi>I will beare the indignation of the Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Micha. 7.9.</note> 
               <hi>becauſe I have ſinned:</hi> And for our parts we have nothing to ſay, God is ſo righteous in all he hath brought upon us, though our calamities be grievous, we may ſee as in a glaſſe ſet before us, both the provoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and the calamities of our deare countrey, in what God moſt juſtly threatned againſt Iſrael,<note place="margin">Deut. 28.47. to 52.</note> if we read 28. <hi>Deut.</hi> from the 47. verſe to the 52. verſe; <hi>Becauſe thou ſervedſt not the Lord thy God with joyfulneſſe, and with gladneſſe of heart, for the abundance of all things, therfore ſhalt thou ſerve thy enemy, which the Lord thy God ſhall ſend a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thee, in hunger and in thirſt, and in nakednes, in want of all things; and he ſhall put a yoke of Iron on thy neck, till he have deſtroyed thee: the Lord ſhall bring a Nation againſt thee from farre, from the end of the earth, as ſwift as the Eagle flieth, a Nation whoſe tongues thou ſhalt not
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:111756:11"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:111756:11"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:111756:12"/>underſtand, a Nation of fierce countenance, which ſhall not regard the perſon of the old, nor ſhew favour to the young: And he ſhall eat the fruit of thy cattell, and the fruit of thy Land untill thou be deſtroyed. And he alſo ſhall not leave thee either corn, or wine, or oyle, or the increaſe of thy kine, or fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ckes of thy ſheep, untill he have deſtroyed thee.</hi> I may ſay this day is this Scripture fulfilled not in our eares only, but in our experience, and in our feares alſo.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, looke on eternitie beyond preſent afflictions, the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle found it an excellent remedy to ſet together in compariſon the life to come, and the glory of it, with this life and its miſeries, 8. <hi>Rom.</hi> 18.<note place="margin">Rom. 8.18.</note> 
               <hi>I reckon that the ſufferings of this preſent life are not worthy of the glory that ſhall be revealed.</hi> And you may ſee more clearly in 2 <hi>Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> 4 16<note place="margin">2 Cor. 4, 16.</note> to the end of the chapter, how excellently this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, Why? <hi>Becauſe we looked not upon things temporall, wee looked on things eternall.</hi> What is it to loſe a houſe, an eſtate, or caſe, or plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, or fine cloathe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>? What is it to loſe all theſe? If we look on things eternall, an inheritance incorruptible and undefiled, that fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth not away, reſerved in heaven, if we look upon things farre more excellent and that eternall weight of glory.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, learn to live by faith upon a promiſe; to live upon a promiſe yet unfilled, there is a quinteſſence and an excellent ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance in a promiſe made by God, to ſupport the heart, though it be not yet fulfilled. And faith h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th an excellent vertue to extract and bring to preſent enjoyment that which is virtualy in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe to comfort and ſtrength then the ſpirit. Faith hath, (if I may ſo ſpeake) a kind of creating power, and can make a man to enjoy that this day that ſhall not be actually accompliſhed, it may be, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny yeares hence, by giving a ſubſiſtance to things future, and an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence to things inviſible,<note place="margin">Heb. 11.1.</note> 11. <hi>Heb.</hi> 1. <hi>Faith is the ſubſtance of things hoped for, the evidence of things not ſeen.</hi> This is an excellencie of faith, That it brings all things to the preſent enjoyment of a belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, even things that are paſt many yeares agoe, and all forgotten; Faith, I ſay, is able to bring them back againe to a Chriſtians pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent uſe and comfort. And things that are on the other ſide farre off to come; Faith can foreſee, and as by a perſpective preſent them to the ſoule as if in being. We ſhould therefore labour to live by faith, as it is promiſed.<note place="margin">Heb. 10.38.</note> 
               <hi>The juſt live by faith, Heb.</hi> 10.38. And as we ſee the Martyrs did,<note place="margin">Heb. 11.13.</note> 
               <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.13. <hi>They looked on the promiſes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>farre
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:111756:12"/>off, and were perſwaded of them</hi> before they came unto them. And as <hi>Abraham</hi> who enjoyed Chriſt in a promiſe,<note place="margin">Joh. 8.56.</note> 
               <hi>Joh.</hi> 8.56. <hi>He ſaw my day and rejoyced,</hi> he ſaw it by faith, and rejoyced in heart, as if he had ſeen it with the eyes of his body. So that there is an excellent Art in Faith (if I may ſo call it) to ſupport the heart of man in time trouble, that if we would make uſe of it, we ſhould be ſo ſtrengthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the day of our calamitie, that we ſhould not ſink. Come we now to the words of the Text, wherein the Prophet, having bridled their too haſty expectation of deliverance in ſo ſhort a time as the falſe Prophets pretended, he goeth about to uphold their faith, that they may wait for deliverance till the appointed time; to which purpoſe,</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, hee ſheweth them the ground whereupon they may build their patience and their hope of deliverance in due time, <hi>verſe</hi> 11.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, he ſheweth them the meanes whereby their delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance hoped for, may be accompliſhed <hi>verſ</hi> 12.13.</p>
            <p>I ſhall undertake onely the former,<note place="margin">The ground.</note> the groond whereupon the Prophet builds their expectation, <hi>Gods thoughts,</hi> concerning which the Prophet holds out two things.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, the manner how theſe thoughts are carried: <hi>I know the thoughts that I think towards you, ſaith the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Secondly, the matter or the reſult of his thoughts, what it is that God intendeth to bring to paſſe in thoſe thoughts, namely, <hi>To give them an expected end.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Before I ſpeake of the manner of the carriage of them, I ſhall ſhew you what theſe thoughts are, then how theſe thoughts of God are carried. Gods thoughts in Scripture principally ſignifie two things. Sometimes they are taken for Gods everlaſting counſels and determinations, that are ſecret. So 33. <hi>Pſal. The counſell of the Lord ſtandeth for ever, and the thoughts of his heart to generations.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 33.11.</note> 
               <hi>Eò ſua conſiliaretulerat:</hi> I know my thoughts, that is to ſay, I know that in my counſels and ſecret determinations,<note place="margin">Non prius de illorum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>xilio, quam de illo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bertate cogitavit. <hi>Sanctius.</hi>
               </note> I am reſolved for your deliverance in due time. And <hi>Sanctius</hi> obſerveth and reſolveth upon theſe words, that God did no ſooner think of, or purpoſe their bondage in Babylon, then he did purpoſe their deliverance and freedome from that captivitie.</p>
            <p>Sometimes Gods thoughts are taken for his word, his revealed will or promiſes, Gods thoughts concerning the Babyloniſh cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivitie,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:111756:13"/>were here as much as Gods will revealed in his word, or Gods promiſes that he had made to his people, concerning their deliverance, and you ſhall ſee, that the promiſe which God calleth here his thoughts,<note place="margin">J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>em. 25 12.</note> is recorded, 25. <hi>Jer.</hi> 12. <hi>And it ſhall come to paſſe when ſeventie yeares are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ccompliſhed, that I will puniſh the King of Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon, and that Nation, ſaith the Lord, for their iniquity, and the Land of the Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ldeans, and will make it perpetuall deſolations. And I will bring you back again to your own Land.</hi> This was the promiſe and the word that God here calleth his thoughts, I know my thoughts. In the mean time theſe thoughts are carried ſomewhat ſecretly, myſteriouſly, and in a hidden way, and therefore though be mean his promiſes and will concerning this matter which are revealed, yet are they called thoughts, which you know are moſt out of ſight: yea, they are called the thoughts of God, the more unſearchable and leſſe to be known: they are thoughts known to God. You know ſomething of God, it may be, but his wayes, much more his thoughts, are paſt finding out, that is to ſay, in what manner or when he will perform his promiſe, though the promiſe it ſelfe may perhaps be known. So that here is the firſt thing inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the ſecret carriage of his thoughts,<note n="*" place="margin">Oppoſition to your thoughts.</note> I know them, that is to ſay, they are things known to me, but they are not known to you; My <hi>thoughts</hi> concerning your deliverance, are unlike <hi>your thoughts,</hi> you think of your deliverance two yeares hence; but I have no ſuch thoughts, ſaith God, my thoughts are otherwiſe, and therfore be ſaith, <hi>I know my thoughts,</hi> your thoughts are, that you ſhall ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly be brought out of bondage, and back to <hi>Jeruſalem:</hi> but, ſaith God, my thoughts are otherwiſe: whereby he intendeth to ſet forth a ſecret Antitheſis, or oppoſition between Gods thoughts, and the thoughts of the Jewes in this time of their captivitie and bondage. From whence the point is.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctrine. </seg>
               </label> Gods thoughts are not as mans thoughts in the paſſages of his providence towards the Church.</p>
            <p>I ſhall not follow this point in the full extent and latitude of it; but only as it is before you in the Text, concerning the Churches afflictions and deliverance out of trouble.</p>
            <p>God hath other thoughts then man hath concerning her afflictions and deliverances. A Patient, you know, under the hand of a Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitian, when he hath ſuffered a great deale of Phyſick, and is much weakned in body, crieth out, Oh I have Phyſick enough, it is high
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:111756:13"/>time I were comforted up again by cordialls, but the wiſe Phiſician may be, hath other thoughts that he muſt yet evacuate more, and bring him lower before he can recover him.</p>
            <p>God is the Phiſician, and the Church is his patient, and ſhe is apt to think, Oh, now wee are weak enough, and brought very low; now it is time for God to deliver: yet it may be God may deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, and that not without cauſe, that the Church ſhall be brought lower yet: the Church hath ſuch thoughts as th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe, if you obſerve, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 74. wherein ſhe complains, as if God had forgotten her,<note place="margin">Pſalm. 74.1.</note> and his covenant, and his enemies, as if God had over-ſlipped the time of her deliverance; the like wee finde of mens thoughts, when God is begun to proceed againſt ſinners in his wrath, they think he will never be reconciled more, he will utterly conſume and caſt off, his covenant ſhall be broken, and there ſhall be an end of all. To ſuch thoughts God anſwers: 55. <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 7.8, 9. <hi>Let the wicked forſake his way, and the unrighteous man his thoughts,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſay 57.7.8, 9</note> 
               <hi>and let him return unto the Lord, and he will have mercy upon him, and to God, for hee will abundantly pardon:</hi> as if God had ſaid, a corrupt man thinks thus of God, becauſe his corrupt heart has not bowels to pardon ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther man, if he ſhall ſo provoke him; ſo meaſuring God by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, but he incourageth them notwithſtanding, to come unto him for pardon, after they have ſo provoked him; <hi>for my thoughts are not your thoughts, nor my wayes your ways; for as the heavens are higher then the earth, ſo are my wayes highter then your ways, and my thoughts then your thoughts.</hi> Alas, mans thoughts are led by outward pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bability, judging of things according to the event of things; Gods thoughts are antecedent to all things, his counſels are from ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting; our thoughts and deſires are many times after a carnall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance of the Church, that wee might have peace and plenty again, but Gods thoughts are more taken up with the ſpirituall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance of his Church and people; he cares not though he leave his people <hi>afflicted and poore,</hi> ſo that he leave them faithfull <hi>th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t will truſt in the name of the Lord, and a holy people that will do no ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity,</hi> 3 <hi>Zeph.</hi> 12. In the 3. of <hi>Ezra</hi> 12. compared with 2. of <hi>Hag.</hi> 7, 8, 9. verſes,<note place="margin">Zeph. 3 12, 13. Ezra 3.12.</note> there is an obſerveable paſſage concerning the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, when the foundation of the later Temple was laid, there was a great deal of ſhouting and joy, but the old Levits, that had ſeen the former Temple, the largeneſs and greatneſs of that Edifice fell a weeping, becauſe they ſaw, that the Temple that was then in
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:111756:14"/>building (the ſecond Temple) was not like to be ſo great and ſo glorious as the former Temple had been; this was mans thought, but God ſaith,<note place="margin">Hag. 2.7, 8 9,.</note> 2. <hi>Hagai</hi> 7, 8, 9 <hi>v. I will fill this houſe with glory, and the later houſe ſhall be greater then the glory of the former houſe;</hi> as if he ſhould have ſaid, you think that I am wanting to my houſe, becauſe I build not ſo great and outwardly glorious a Temple as I did before, thats nothing ſaith God, my thoughts are not on the outward Temple, but I mean to make this later Temple a great deal more glorious and honourable then the former, becauſe I will make it glorious with a ſpirituall glory, the former Temple, how goodly ſoever it was in building, never had Chriſt in it; but this later Temple ſhall have Chriſt in it, that ſhall make it more honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable and more glorious then the other Temple was; even ſo it is here: many times our thoughts are carnall thoughts, concerning the Churches deliverance and affliction, they are carryed to out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward things, we would faine be as we were, trading as it was, plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty as it was, theſe are the things we look on: whereas God hath other thoughts, it may be he would have us a more honourable people another way, he would have us more zealous and holy then ever we were, to honour us with more of the Kingdom of Chriſt then before, to make us richer in the work of Reformation and in ſpirtuall things then we were before in temporall things.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>1</label> Firſt, becauſe he would have the Churches deliverance to be brought in unto her in a way of faith above humane probability, which it could not be, if it ſhould come by ſenſe and reaſon, and that we could alwayes judge of the carriage of things, if things were carried in our own way, how ready ſhould we be to ſacrifice to our own wiſdome and power, and therefore the Lord will make fooliſh mans wiſdom, and make mens ſtrength weakneſs, and will carry on his work by ſuch means as men think are inconſiderable to his own ends: 7. <hi>Judges</hi> 20. the Lord had by providence put into the hands of <hi>Gideon</hi> a conſiderable army againſt the <hi>Midianites,</hi> they were thirty two thouſand,<note place="margin">Judg. 7.20.</note> but God cometh to him and tells him, <hi>theſe are too many for mee to deliver the Midianites into thy hands,</hi> for if I deliver the <hi>Midianites</hi> into the hands of ſo many, they will ſay, <hi>Iſrael ſaved themſelves,</hi> and theſe men did the work, and theſe ſhall carry away all the glory of the day; and therefore, ſaith God, I cannot with ſafety of my own honour deliver into their hands the <hi>Midianites,</hi> God could with more ſafety deliver them into the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:111756:14"/>hands of three hundred, then into the hands of thirty two thouſand, for then all the world muſt needs be convinced, and ſay, This was the very finger of God, and a ſpeciall work of the Almighty; And indeed, my Brethren, we are never brought throughly to give God his honour in ſuch things as theſe, while we are in wayes of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>babilitie, while we are in hope through humane ſtrength. The Prophet obſerving ſuch a diſpoſition in the <hi>Jewes;</hi> namely, that they would not acknowledge Gods hand, unleſſe they were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced into ſtraits that ſhould make them hopeleſſe, tells them, 37. <hi>Ezech.</hi> 12, 13. They ſhould be as good as dead in <hi>Babylon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezech 37.12, 13.</note> wel-nigh buried in that captivity, but God would deliver them thence, and, <hi>when I have opened your graves,</hi> ſaid God, <hi>and brought you back out of your graves again, then ſhall yee know that I am the Lord;</hi> you would not know before, but then ſhal you know that I am the Lord.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>2</label> Secondly, becauſe it becometh God Almighty to walk in an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary way, ſutable to his infinite Majeſty, not as men, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to rules of reaſon and power, and humane wiſdome, when the Apoſtle cometh to ſpeak of God his wayes and counſels, queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and wonders, <hi>Oh, how unſearchable are his Judgements, and his wayes paſt finding out?</hi> 11. Rom. 33.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom. 11.33.</hi> Eſt in rebus, nec tamen eſt inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, eſt extra res, nec tamen eſt excluſus, <hi>Auguſt.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>It is like God, when we ſay of him, he is incomprehenſible, God is in things, yet not included, and he is without things, yet not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded; ſo it is done like the Almighty, when he doth not according to humane rules of policy and prudence, but when he doth things be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond all grounds of expectation, of wiſdome and reaſon, therefore the Lord is ſaid to have his way in the whirle-wind,<note place="margin">Nah. 1.3. Pſal. 77.19.</note> 1. <hi>Nah.</hi> 3. <hi>and his footſteps are not known,</hi> 77. Pſal. 19.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>1</label> This at once offereth both a check and remedy unto our car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall preſumptions, and our carnall feares: carnall preſumption is a diſeaſe that we are often ſick of in theſe dayes, when as God is pleaſed to ſmile on us a little in our trouble and miſery, to give us ſome revivings, then are we too apt to be too much lifted up, too hold in our confidence; and to conclude, too peremptorily. Let us take the check which the Lord giveth us here: <hi>My thoughts are not as your thoughts,</hi> and therefore ſaucily talk no more of your thoughts in the ways of God, Gods ways are above your wayes, his thoughts above your thoughts. God hath cleerly given our thoughts the check in four<note n="*" place="margin">Four things wherein God hath checked our preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous thoghts touching our preſent troubles.</note> things concerning theſe troubles, which we ought to receive and take notice of, as ſo many convictions of this truth
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:111756:15"/>and occaſions of reflecting upon our ſelves with ſhame and ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row this day.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, we thought, that if we had to our enemies thoſe that were Gods enemies, then we muſt needs quickly overcome them, and that becauſe our enemies are Gods enemies, ſwearing enemies, drunken enemies, Popiſh enemies, Atheiſticall enemies, prophane enemies, we conclude, God will never favour them, nor ſuffer them to prevaile, nor deliver his people into their hands; but beſide our owne experience on the contrary, we find that <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maleck,</hi> the worſt of all the enemies that Iſrael had, a people as much abhorred of God as any, yet if <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſhall tranſgreſſe, <hi>Ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leck</hi> ſhall prevaile, if Iſrael will not pray, not ſeek unto God, not humble themſelves, all the wickedneſſe of the <hi>Amaleckites</hi> ſhall not deſtroy them,<note place="margin">Exod. 17.11.</note> 17. <hi>Exod</hi> 11. The proud <hi>Aſſyrian,</hi> that boaſting wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked enemie, God had j<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſtice and wrath enough in ſtore for them, yet God will not medle with, then they ſhall go on and oppreſs Iſrael, till Iſrael be reformed, till the work be done upon mount Sion, and on Jeruſalem, God will not ſtrike a ſtroke againſt Aſſyria for their ruine, but will ſuffer them to prevaile, 10. <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 12. Nay, if Gods people continue impenitent, and remain in their wickedneſſe, God will then ſtrengthen the hands of their enemies,<note place="margin">Iſai. 10.12.</note> 3. <hi>Judg.</hi> 12. When Iſrael had ſinned, ſaith the Text, <hi>the Lord ſtrengthened the hands of Eglon againſt Iſrael, becauſe they had done evill in the ſight of the Lord.</hi> We ſhould not run too much on that ſtrain. Our enemies are wicked and prophane enemies, (its true) and God will plague and puniſh them: But let us not make that a ground of our too much confidence &amp; boldnes. God may both ſuffer and ſtrengthen them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt us, if wee remaine an unreformed and a rebellious people; we have hitherto felt and found them as goads in our ſides, and thornes in our eyes. Our thoughts have therein deceived us.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, we are ſo taken up with the thoughts of a good cauſe, that we cannot admit a thought of miſcarrying.<note place="margin">A good cauſe may miſcarry <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d tempus.</hi>
               </note> I grant, in the iſſue it ſhall prevaile, and finally, and we may conclude as much in the generall. But take heed of concluding peremptorily for particular times, as that we ſhould conclude ſo of this time, and of theſe enemies; that we ſhall overcome at this day, or in this gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration; who can ſay ſo? A good cauſe may yet have a prevailing enemy a l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng time; and the people of God may have a good cauſe, and yet flie before their enemies. Obſerve a cleare inſtance in the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:111756:15"/>people of Iſrael they went againſt the children of <hi>Benjamin,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Judg. 20.18.</note> 
               <hi>Judg.</hi> 20.18. A good cauſe they had, and they were ſo bold thereon, that when they came to go againſt the <hi>Benjamites,</hi> they did not ſo much as ask the Lord, whether they ſhould goe or no. But the firſt que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion they make, is, Which of us ſhall go up firſt, as taking it for granted, their cauſe was ſo good, they muſt needs prevaile, onely they would be ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tialled by the Lord: But yet for all their good cauſe they flie before their enemies,<note place="margin">Verſ. 21.25.</note> you may ſee once at the 21. verſe, and againe, at verſe 25. Therfore build not too much upon the cauſe, as if the preſent iſſue of things did depend barely on that: Deliverance in time ſhall come, which may be a comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble encouragement to goe on in a good cauſe. But let us not li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit the holy One of Iſrael, the cauſe in which we ſuffer, is as ſure to conquer, as the light is to ſhine, being Gods, and therefore ſhall prevaile at length. But a good cauſe may be ill managed, and ſuffer for the ſins of thoſe that undertake it, and in this alſo we have had experience of the vanitie of our thoughts, we are not yet delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, though our cauſe be good.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, another thing we have too high thoughts upon, and wherein Gods thoughts are otherwiſe, is the priviledge of out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ordinances: Bleſſed be the name of our God, that we have the liberty we have, and that God hath taken off the yoke of the oppreſſor, wherein our conſciences were burthened with more then Egyptian bondage; yet ſhould we be humbled that this out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward priviledge in Gods ordinances hath too much lifted up our thoughts, and we have been too confident upon them, becauſe we have the miniſtery of the word more purified, and ſome ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons purged out from the worſhip of God among us, we have thoughts, that therefore we ſhall now prevail, our enemies ſhall be conſumed before us, notwithſtanding many other our yet latent ſinnes. See what in the like caſe did befall the Iſraelites, when the Philiſtines came againſt them, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 4.3.5.<note place="margin">1. Sam. 4.3, 5</note> 
               <hi>And when the people of God were come into the Camp, the Elders of Iſrael ſaid, Wherefore hath the Lord ſmitten us to day before the Philiſtines? Let us f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tch the Ark of the Covenant of the Lord out of Shiloh unto us, that when it commeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us, it may ſave us out of the hand of our enemies. And when the Ark of the Covenant of the Lord came into the camp, all Iſrael ſhouted with a great ſhout, ſo that the earth rang againe.</hi> At the 10. and 11 verſ. <hi>And the Philiſtines fought, and Iſrael was ſmitten, and they fled every
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:111756:16"/>man to his tent: and there was a very great ſlaughter, for there fell of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael thirty thouſand footmen. And the Ark of God was taken, and the two Sonnes of Eli, Hophni and Phinehas were ſlain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Ark, though it was the outward Teſtimonie of Gods preſence, it would not bear them out they were ſlain before the enemy with a great ſlaughter, and the Arke of God was taken. I ſpeake not this, that this ſhould any way weaken our love, or our thankfulneſſe to God for thoſe outward Priviledges we enjoy, or that we ſhould any way leſſen our eſteeme and reverence of Gods ordinances, but that we ſhould not make them, nor any thing elſe a ground of carnall confidence, that we ſhould build our ſelves up in vaine hope, and ſet our ſelves upon a deceitfull expectation, That the very outward ordinances ſhould deliver us from outward af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions and temporall puniſhments that may bee on us by the hand of God. In this alſo we have found that God hath checked our thoughts, and brought us low before our enemies, that would captivate our religion, as the Philiſtines did the Ark.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/>
               <note place="margin">The L: <hi>Brook,</hi> M. <hi>Hambden,</hi> M. <hi>Pym, &amp;c.</hi>
               </note>Fourthly, in our thoughts touching thoſe worthy and pretious inſtruments whom God had raiſed up to carry on his work among 01 us: we thought it had been they that ſhould have delivered us, ſome by th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ir counſels, and others by their valour, being ſo choicely fitted inſtruments, that we looked upon each of them as an <hi>Atlas</hi> to our cauſe and Kingdome, and ſuch pillars of the reformation, as that without them it could not have been ſupported or carried on: Yet all this while that we were idolizing his ſervants, God intended to do his work by other hands then we looked on, and that <hi>Moſes</hi> ſhould not bring the Iſraelites into the land of Canaan (though he was a man called and excellently fitted to lead them thitherward) but when <hi>Moſes</hi> was dead, he was able, and ſo raiſed up <hi>Joſhua,</hi> with whom he would be, and was as effectually to all purpoſes, as he was wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h <hi>Moſes</hi> And I may appeale unto you all, whether God hath been wanting to his cauſe, through or ſince the taking a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way of ſuch famous men as have appeared for us; or whether he hath not carried on the work more ſtrenouſly ſince: he that had ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit to make ſuch inſtruments, hath ſpirit enough to raiſe up more, as we have ſeen ſo that in this alſo we have ſeen God checking our thoughts: And as it is a check, it ſhould be looked upon likewiſe as a remedy, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſhould be enough to cure our preſumption, to think on this Doctrine, <hi>Gods thoughts are not as our thoughts.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:111756:16"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">A check to carnall fears in times of trouble.</note>It may as well afford us a checke and a cure to our carnall feares: for as we are too bold on the one hand, we are too weak ſpirited on the other in times of afflictions, and when Gods hand is yet out againſt us, we are as full of deſperate feares, as before we were full of ſaucie preſumptions. And in our jealouſies conclude, there is no recovery, no hope, or expectation left for the people of God; whereas Gods thoughts (may be) are otherwiſe, even to carry on his ends by weak means, and when his people are loweſt to raiſe them, when things are deſperate and all paſt cure, then God thinks to worke: for hee worketh <hi>not by power, nor by might, but by my ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,</hi> ſaith God, 4. <hi>Zach.</hi> 6. He giveth not <hi>the battell to the ſtrong,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Z<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ch. 4.6. Ezek. 9.11.</note> 
               <hi>nor the race to the ſwift,</hi> but to whom he pleaſeth, 9. <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 11. God many times layeth the foundation of ſome great deliverance very low, out of ſight, and (as it were) under ground: The foundation that God laid for the deliverance and preſervation of the Church of Iſrael in Egypt, (you may obſerve) was the ſelling of <hi>Joſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ph</hi> by his brethren. A ſtrange foundation. So likewiſe, Gods providence had a hand in turning away <hi>David</hi> from the Philiſtines Armie; wherein God beyond all imagination intended to prevent <hi>David,</hi> leſt he ſhould have his hand in the blood of <hi>Saul,</hi> who was ſlain by the Philiſtines ſhortly after <hi>David</hi> was gone from them, as is obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 29, 30, &amp; 31. chapters. Yea, we find God had another reach in bringing away <hi>David</hi> from the Philiſtines Armie: for there was need of <hi>Davids</hi> ſervice at Ziglag, becauſe that was taken ſhortly after, and therefore <hi>David</hi> was come away by the hand of Providence, to ſerve for the reſcue of that town, and of his wives, that were taken priſoners there. We ſhould therefore in times of danger, when there is the leaſt likelihood of ſafetie or deliverance, we ſhould ſtay our hearts againſt all carnall feares, by caſting our ſelves upon God, who worketh in unknown wayes, even as we ſee by thoſe ſtories, beyond all imagination.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Remedies a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganſt carnall feares.</note>Give me leave to propoſe unto you theſe 3 remarkable things, to carry up the ſoules of men from being tranſported with carnall feares in times of danger.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, conſider Gods unchangeable love to his Church, even when ſhee is in perſecution, he is in love with her when we think he hath caſt her off, even while ſhee is in the furnace of afflictions, God ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ith of her, <hi>I have choſen thee in the furnace of affliction,</hi> 48. Iſa. 9, 10. That may bear us up againſt fear that God is alway un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeable in his love to his Church.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:111756:17"/>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, his uninterrupted preſence with the Church, what ever her afflictions be, and that makes her invincible, ſo the holy Prophet inferres,<note place="margin">Pſal. 46.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 46. Pſal. 5. <hi>God is in the midst of her, therefore ſhee ſhall not be moved, God ſhall help her, and that right early;</hi> though it ſhould be in a time when the Sea roared, and the earth ſhould be moved, and the mountains ſhould be c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rried into the midſt of the Sea,<note place="margin">Verſe 2. 3.</note> Verſ. 2.3.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, conſider Gods promiſes of making every thing (even the bittereſt of her afflictions) to work togeth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r for her good, 8. <hi>Rom.</hi> 28. So I paſs from the former branch in the manner of the carriage of Gods thoughts,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.38.</note> that they were carried in a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret way, unlike, yea, oppoſite to the thoughts of the <hi>Jewes,</hi> Your thoughts are to be delivered after two yeers captivity, or ſhortly, but <hi>I know my thoughts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Another branch, of the manner of the carriage of theſe thoughts, they were carried, ſo as that they were unlike to his own car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage towards them, which did ſpeak nothing but miſery and deſolation; hee had clad himſelf with vengeance as with a garment, he had put on zeal as a cloak, he had taken the ſword in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his hand, he had given them up into the hands of his enemies, and he tells of a bondage and ſlavery in which they ſhould lie threeſcore and ten yeers; here was nothing but ſeverity and wrath, to be ſeen or heard from God; his ways toward his people at this time, gave ſo little incouragement to hope that hee had any good purpoſes toward them at preſent, that the <hi>Septuagint</hi> tranſlate theſe thoughts of peace in the future, not in the preſent Tenſe, <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gitabo ſuper vos cogitationem pacis.</hi> And yet, even now (ſaith God) for all that, My thoughts toward you are thoughts of peace, I know my thoughts that I think toward you, though my carriage be thus, hard, puniſhing, and wrathfull; whence the next point for obſervation is this:</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctr. </seg>
               </label> Gods bowels are full of love and compaſſion toward his people, even when he is driven to bring upon them his heavieſt judgements, <hi>Deus it<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> punit rebellem populum, ut illius non adjiciat curam;</hi> Before we come to confirm the point, give me leave to premiſe ſome Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions by way of Caution or Conceſſion.<note place="margin">C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſions.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, that God may turn away in diſpleaſure from his people, though they be his own inheritance,<note place="margin">Pſal. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 1.</note> 60. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 1.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, his people may apprehend poſſibly, that Gods love is
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:111756:17"/>quite extinguiſhed toward them, and that all is ſhut up in diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure; you ſee it was ſo with Chriſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 27.46. <hi>My God, my God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 27.46.</note> 
               <hi>why haſt thou forſaken me?</hi> and therefore much more may it be with any other man: and <hi>David</hi> cryeth out,<note place="margin">Pſal. 77.7.</note> 77. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 7. <hi>That God was gone, and he would never return, he had ſhut up his loving kindneſs in diſpleaſure for ever,</hi> though he was miſtaken.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, yet at ſuch a time Gods bowels are ful of love and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion towards his, though they be ſo ſorely afflicted: mark what a ſoul-warming expreſſion the Lord hath given concerning his Church in her afflictions, even when hee had delivered his people into the hands of their curſed enemies,<note place="margin">Jerem. 12.7.</note> 12. <hi>Jerem.</hi> 7. <hi>I have deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered the dearly beloved of my ſoul into the hands of her enemies:</hi> though Gods people, and the dearly beloved of his ſoul, and unto him as a Jewell of great price, hee ſuffered them to be trampled un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the uncircumciſed feet of the <hi>Moabites</hi> and <hi>Idumeans</hi> for a time. Anger in God is not a paſſion, as it is in man, that it ſhould overwhelm all his love, and caſt out all his bowels toward them; no, it doth ſo indeed with us, and that is our corruption, our ſin, we cannot be angry but we weaken our love, but it is not ſo with God; for his love is as eſſentiall to him as other attributes, and therefore being of Gods eſſence, they are continued ſtill in act, as I may ſay, and muſt needs be conſiſtent; nay, further, the love of God towards his Church, is the ſupreme attribute of God toward his Church, and all Gods diſpenſations and carriages in the at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributes ſhall be ſubordinate to his love which hee bears to his Church; if hee plague them, if he puniſh them, if he give them into the hands of their enemies, if hee bring famine or the plague,<note place="margin">Demonſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Gods love to his people, even in his puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of them.</note> or the ſword upon them, he can, and will do all theſe things in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordination to his love, which ſhall be the ſoveraign a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tribute that ſhall ſteer all theſe, and bring them to a concluſion of mercy and loving kindneſs at laſt, whereof there are three demonſtrations.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, all his Judgements that hee brings on his Church are diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſed Euangelically, as m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y appeare in that they come from an Euangelicall gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>und or principle; they are not the fruits or effects of Juſtice properly,<note place="margin">Heb. 12.7, 8.11.</note> but they proceed fromk Gods love and father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly care of his people, 12. <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.7, 8, 11. verſes, in all the ſufferings that he brought on them, God dealt with them as with children, ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>Whom the Lord l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>veth he chaſteneth, and ſcourgeth every one wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m he receiveth; if yee indure obaſtening, God dealeth with
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:111756:18"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:111756:18"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:111756:19"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:111756:19"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:111756:20"/>you as with ſonnes.</hi> And as they come from an Euangelicall ground, ſo all Gods judgements do aim at an Euangelicall end, even the benefit of his people; they aim not at the deſtruction of any, but at the humbling, ſanctifying, and ſaving of his people, that is, at leaſt, <hi>finis operantis,</hi> 27. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 9. The Lord in afflicting the Church, is as a Phyſician,<note place="margin">Iſa. 27.9.</note> all that he looks for, is a purging of them from their uncleanneſſes, from their ſins and corruptions, and if that be taken away, he lookes for no more, <hi>By this ſhall the iniquity of Jacob be purged, and this is all the fruit, the taking away of his ſin;</hi> and hee cleerly tels you, his end is their ſalvation, <hi>that they might not be condemned with the world,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 11.32.</note> 1 Cor. 11.32. Moreover, they are diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſed Euangelically, as appeareth in the meaſure of their afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and from the manner of the carriage of them, when they are at the worſt, when Gods hand is ſevereſt on his people, yet ſee at that very time, God he doth differ in the manner and in the meaſure of puniſhing them and his enemies: For thus God appeals (and it was in an affliction that was very heavie on his people) 27. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 7, 8. ſaith God,<note place="margin">Iſa. 27.7, 8.</note> It is true, your afflictions are very grievous, ſo that they were to be left deſolate, yet I appeal to your ſelves (though you might in this caſe be partial) <hi>Have I corrected you, as I have corrected your enemies? Have I ſmitten you, as I have ſmitten them?</hi> Can you ſay, I have not made a difference between the Rods that I have laid on you, and the Rods I brought on them?</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, hee calleth on the Church to believe in him, even when ſhe is moſt ſeverely corrected, and under his puniſhing hand, which ſhe could not, neither would God call her to do, if all his bowels were ſhrunk, and all his love toward her were utterly end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in diſpleaſure; Fear not <hi>Jacob,</hi> he incourageth her, 43. <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> from the 1. to the 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi> verſe,<note place="margin">Iſa. 34.1.7.</note> 
               <hi>When thou paſſeſt through the waters, I will be with thee, and through the rivers, they ſhall not overflow thee; when thou walkest through the fire, thou ſhalt not be burnt, neither ſhall the flame kindle upon thee:</hi> and hee calls on the Church, that ſhee ſhould believe and depend on God, and in the time of her troubles hee had a love to her therefore, which he would have the Church rely upon; and indeed the Church could not rely on him, nor be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve in him, if ſo be there were not ſuch an attribute in God, as love, and tender bowels of compaſſion toward her actually at that time; for pure wrath and diſpleaſure in God would dutterly deſtroy faith, and not exerciſe it, for there can be no believing in God by
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:111756:20"/>any, where there is not ſome love in God toward them; but faith is exerciſed by the Church in the times of her ſoreſt calamitie, as is obſervable, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 63.15, 16.<note place="margin">Iſai. 63.10, 10, 15, 16.</note> though God was now afflicting them heavily: <hi>For he was turned to be their enemy, and he fought againſt them;</hi> yet the Church, even then, ſtrongly apprehended his love and rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion towards them, as appeares in their expoſtulation with God. <hi>Where is thy zeale and thy ſtrength, the ſounding of thy bowels, and of thy mercies towards me? Are they reſtrained? Doubtleſſe thou art our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, though Abraham be ignorant of us, and Iſrael acknowledgeth us not, thou, O Lord, art our Father, our Redeemer, thy name is from everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, the yearning of his bowels: when he is driven to afflict his Church, he doth it with a great deale of tender heartedneſſe, as a man may ſay, and reluctancie, his compaſſions are ſtirred up with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in him, and he looks out for the firſt return of his people by repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, that he may have an occaſion, and take the firſt hop of an op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity to be merciful to them. Nay, ſuch is the Lords compaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on toward them, as that he proteſteth, <hi>Hee is afflicted in all their affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, Iſai.</hi> 63.9. though he afflict,<note place="margin">Iſa. 63.9.</note> he feels (as it were) every ſtroke that is laid on them: And on may obſerve in this kind, a ſtrange declaration of Gods bowels, <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.20.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ier.</hi> 31.20.</note> When <hi>Ephraim</hi> had been ſmitten by God, and God had ſeen <hi>Ephraim</hi> repenting, and ſmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting on his thigh, humbling and bemoaning himſelf, Gods bowels were turned in him for <hi>Ephraim: For ſince I ſpake againſt him, I doe earneſtly remember him ſtill, therefore my bowels are troubled for him; I will ſurely have mercy upon him, ſaith the Lord.</hi> As if a mother ſhould ſtand in a corner for a while, and hide herſelfe from her child, and heare the child weeping and bemoaning himſelfe, O my mother, my mother is gone, ſhe cannot withhold long, but muſt come in, and ſhew her ſelf unto the child. And if natural parents that are e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill, can be ſo tender over their children in their miſery, how much more are there infinite bowels in God toward his people, even when he afflicteth them?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>1</label> Firſt, there cannot be a better, or more encouraging motive, to ſeeke the Lord in the time of our troubles, then this, That hee car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rieth ſuch bowels of love and mercie, and that he is ſo ready to melt toward his people in the times of their ſoreſt judgements. Oh how ſhould this melt our hearts in Gods preſence this day! Whoſe heart doth not as it were weep within him? and is not ſomewhat ſofte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:111756:21"/>when he conceiveth that the Almighty, our God before whom we lie this day, is thus bigge with mercie, and as I may ſay, in pain till he be delivered; he would fain be mercifull to England, he would fain be mercifull to his people. O then my brethren! give God way, humble your ſouls before the Lord, caſt down your ſelves.<note place="margin">Levit. 26.40, 41, and 42.</note> You heard ere-while, <hi>Levit.</hi> 26.40, 41, &amp; 42. ver. That the Lord did but look for a time that his people would accept of their puniſhment, and lie low before him, that hee might remember his covenant with <hi>Abraham,</hi> and his covenant with <hi>Iſaac,</hi> and his cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant with <hi>Jacob</hi> our Fathers. O therfore ſhrink not up the bowels of the Lord this day. If we ſhall not humble our ſouls before him, upon ſo ſweet and Evangelicall a motive as this is, I teſtifie to you this day, that we are guilty of ſhrinking up the Lords bowels to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward us, we are guiltie of ſhutting up his compaſſions when hee would be mercifull to us, we are guilty of our owne deſtruction, as God ſaid to Iſrael, <hi>Hoſea</hi> 13.9. <hi>O Iſrael thy deſtruction is from thy ſelf,</hi> ſaith God,<note place="margin">Hoſea 13.9.</note> 
               <hi>but in me is thine help.</hi> I would have helped thee, but thou wouldeſt not come unto me, thou wouldeſt not labour to bee prepared for my help, to be capable of my love, ſo may God ſay to us, if when he hath offered us ſo many tenders of ſalvation, and given us ſo many experiences of his goodneſſe, love and power to us, and to his cauſe: if after all this, we will not humble our ſouls, and labour to draw out theſe bowels more and more to carry on this deliverance, to finiſh what he hath begun, we ſhall certainly, I ſay, be guiltie of all our own woe &amp; miſery; there is great need now of every mans improving himſelfe as farre as he can, to draw out theſe tender bowels of the Almighty toward this poore kingdom: Ireland is already over-run and laid waſt; and the poore remnant there, are deſigned as ſheep to the ſlaughter. Behold the bleeding condition of England, bleeding (alas) to death if it be not preven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Do you not look on the deſolations made in many parts of the Kingdom already? And which is yet a greater miſery, Is not Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land a divided Kingdom? a divided Citie? how can it ſtand? how can it con inue? Therfore if you have any pity toward a dying king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, if any comp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſion to your deare Countrey; if you have any love to God, any to the Religion we profeſſe, and to the cauſe of Chriſt, labour to draw out theſe divine bowels. God would readily open his bowels toward England, Oh ſhrink them not up, let us not harden Gods heart againſt us, by hardening ours againſt him,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:111756:21"/>and againſt his judgements now abroad in the world.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Directions to draw forth Gods bowels toward us.</note>The better to inſtruct us how to draw out theſe bowels toward us, and to prepare us, that God may extend and exerciſe his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſions toward us in our preſent affliction, which hee carries to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward his people when his hand is upon them, I ſhall preſent you three Directions, viz.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, ſee that we caſt away all carnall confidences: God will har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den his heart againſt us, if we truſt in the arme of fleſh, as he did a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his people formerly, in the like caſe, as we ſee <hi>Iſai.</hi> 31.1. <hi>Woe to them that goe down to Egypt for help, and ſtay on horſes, and truſt in Chariots, becauſe they are many, and in Horſemen, becauſe they are very ſtrong.</hi> And Iſai. 30.2, 3. <hi>That walke to goe downe into Egypt (and have not asked at my mouth) to ſtrengthen themſelves in the ſtrength of Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raoh, and to truſt in the ſhadow of Egypt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſaiah 31.1.</note> 
               <hi>Therefore ſhall the ſtrength of Pharaoh be your ſhame, and the truſt in the ſhadow of Egypt, your confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</hi> The Lord withdrew himſelfe from his peoples help, even for their truſting in lying vanities, and turned that w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> they truſted in, into their ſhame, and proteſted he would deliver them no more, if they ſhould continue to withdraw their truſt from him, as hee had delivered Iſrael when oppreſſed by the Zidonians, and the Amale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kites, and the Maonites, <hi>Judg.</hi> 10.13, 14. <hi>Ye have forſaken mee,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Judg. 10.13, 14.</note> 
               <hi>and ſerved other Gods, wherefore I will deliver you no more, goe and cry unto the Gods which ye have choſen, let them deliver you in the time of your trouble.</hi> We have been going downe to Egypt alſo too much, ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding on horſes, and truſting in the ſtrength of men, we have had our confidences in our Armies, and wiſe men, and gallant ſpirits, and the Lord hath hardened his heart againſt us hitherto. But if wee place our whole affiance in the Lord, renouncing all creature-confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, his heart wil melt towards us, and his bowels yearn upon us, as they did upon Iſrael when they renounced Aſhur,<note place="margin">Hoſ. 14.3, 4.</note> 
               <hi>Hoſea</hi> 14.3, 4. <hi>Aſhur ſhall not ſave us, we will not ride upon horſes:</hi> he an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſweres, <hi>I will heale their back-ſlidings, I will love them freely: for mine anger is turned away.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The ſecond means how to draw out theſe bowels of Gods com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion toward us, will be, that we hold on in the duty of ſoul hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation, of ſeeking unto God by faſting and praying, repenting of our ſins, and turning from our evill wayes, for it is thereupon that the Lord promiſeth to return and be mercifull, 1. <hi>Zachariah</hi> 3. nor let any perſwade you, that this duty of confeſſion, and godly
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:111756:22"/>ſorrow for ſinne is an antiquated duty, or now out of date, ſince Chriſt came in the fleſh, it is a duty continued ſtill; It is a Goſpel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duty, and not only required under the Law,<note place="margin">Jame<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 4.10. 1 Pet. 5.6.</note> ſee 4. <hi>James,</hi> 10. and in 1 <hi>Peter</hi> 5.6. it is required of Believers, and charged upon them that are in Chriſt, as having ſtill need to humble themſelves under the mighty hand of God, that he may raiſe them up: Hold on there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to ſeek the Lord while hee may be found, to call upon him while he is neer: <hi>Let the wicked forſake his way, and the unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous man his thoughts, and let him return unto the Lord, and hee will have mercy upon him, and to our God, for bee will abundantly pardon,</hi> Iſaiah 55.6, 7.<note place="margin">Iſa. 55.6.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, Prayer openeth the bowels of the Lord towards his Church and People, eſpecially when it followeth upon humiliati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: <hi>If they humble themſelves and pray,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Chron. 7.14.</note> 2 Chron. 7.14. <hi>Then I will hear in heaven, forgive their ſins, and heal their land,</hi> if they humble themſelves and pray; prayer in this poſture, is that that will provoke the Lord to return and be mercifull, when other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe he is reſolved to ſit ſtill:<note place="margin">Hoſ. 5.15.</note> As you ſee, <hi>Hoſea</hi> 5.15. <hi>I will go and return to my place, till they acknowledge their offence, and ſeek my face.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>2</label> Seeing that God is full of bowels and compaſſion toward his people, even in the midſt of thoſe heavie afflictions that he brings on them, with what comfort (my beloved Brethren) may we not only heare, but alſo feele this truth made good unto us this day, in the midſt of our miſeries and calamities? God is pleaſed to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member mercy in the midſt of judgements, and to give us a little reviving in our bondage, together with ſome ſweet experiences of his power and faithfulneſs: we ſhould be exceedingly raiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d up in our confidence toward God, when wee conſider, how the Lord hath made good unto us that promiſe anciently made to his Church, <hi>Zech.</hi> 8.19.<note place="margin">Zech. 8.19.</note> 
               <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord of Hoaſt, The faſt of the fourth Moneth, and the faſt of the fifth, and the faſt of the ſeventh, and the faſt of the tenth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dayes of pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries God had given the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament forces in <hi>Hampſhire, Yorkeſhire,</hi> and <hi>Wales.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>ſhall be to the houſe of Judah joy and gladneſs, and cheerfull feaſts; therefore love the truth and peace.</hi> The faſtings of our former moneths have they not of late been, if not turned into, yet at leaſt mingled with feaſtings of joy, and dayes of Thankſgiving? Since we have ſuch experience, not only that there are ſuch bowels of love in God, but alſo that they yearn toward us in our miſery, let us indeavour to improve them, ſo as that Gods thoughts of peace may be carryed on toward that <hi>expected end</hi> which God hath
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:111756:22"/>purpoſed concerning his peoples calamities; and the rather, ſeeing God is now going out before us, and hath put himſelf into a poſture of deliverance; let us go about to improve our deliverances, that God hath been pleaſed to beſtow upon us.</p>
            <p>It is ſaid of <hi>Hanibal,</hi> that he knew how to conquer, but he knew not how to improve his victories: in like manner,<note place="margin">Hannibal.</note> God is pleaſed to give us victories, but we know not how to improve them as we might. We love to heare the good newes of ſucceſſes againſt the enemies of God and his Cauſe; we delight to heare of deliverance, but when through Gods goodneſs we hear thereof, we ſit ſtill, and deliverance leaveth us where it findeth us, we are never the more improved, nor a whit inlarged toward God, nor more capable of a finall deliverance thereby; let us learn at length, how we may car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry on our deliverance,<note place="margin">Directions to improve par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances.</note> and improve every victory toward the full deliverance of the Church of God; for which purpoſe I ſhall ſet before you ſome few following directions.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, when a deliverance is up, drive it on by prayer; it was a ſpirituall policy (if I may call it ſo) that when God began to deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the people of <hi>Iſrael</hi> out of their bondage, they did not ſlack, but improve their duty of prayer, the more hee delivered, the more they prayed,<note place="margin">Pſal. 126.1.</note> 
               <hi>Pſal.</hi> 126.1. the Lord had begun to turn the captivity of <hi>Babylon, When the Lord turned again the captivity of Sion, then were we like unto them that dream,</hi> the deliverance was ſo great, as that they durſt hardly believe their own ſenſe and experience therof, but were as in a dream;<note place="margin">Verſe 4.</note> yet <hi>verſe</hi> 4. they make it matter of their farther prayer, <hi>Turn again our captivity as the rivers in the South,</hi> as thou haſt begun to turn the ſtream of our captivity, turn it as the ſtreams in the South, which do ſatisfie the dry and thirſty land in thoſe parts, ſo turn thou our captivity, till thou haſt fully accompliſhed the work of our deliverance: Eſpecially when God giveth us deliveran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces as the fruit of our prayer, we have great cauſe then to proſecute and purſue our victories by our prayers; and for our late ſucceſſes, God hath given them as the fruit of prayer, and in them God hath viſibly returned an anſwer to all the cries and armies of ſupplicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that have been ſent up on our faſting dayes to the throne of Grace, and therefore you ſhould follow it, as you know the holy Ghoſt directeth us, <hi>Pſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l.</hi> 65.2. <hi>O thou that heareſt prayer, unto thee ſhall all fleſh come;</hi> when God manifeſteth himſelf to his peoples experience, that he is a prayer-hearing God, he doth in effect incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage all men to wait upon him in prayer.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:111756:23"/>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, the more God cometh unto us by deliverances, let us the more draw neer to God by dep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ndancy; there is a curſed diſpoſition in the heart, namely, to r ſt in them. when God hath given us any deliverances, as either glutting our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uſts by injoying the fleſhly delights of them, or through pride and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>elf-love, having our turns ſerved upon God for the preſent, wee care for no more, and affect a kinde of ind<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pendancy, uſing God (as <hi>Themiſteeles</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained the people uſed him) like a Plane tree, whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ople run un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to for a ſhelter in a ſtorm, but at another time neglect it, pluck off her leaves; or as ſome men uſe Phyſicians, only while they are ſick, but when they are recovered &amp; in health, look not after them: thus are we alſo apt to deale with God when he hath delivered us from ſome particular diſtreſs, we let go our hold on God, and abate our zeal in following him by prayers and ſupplications, as if we needed him not now as before, and were reſolved not to ſeek him any more, till a new diſtreſs ſhould drive us to him, and ſo to ſeek him, not out of any love to him, or deſire of his honour, but meerly out of concupiſcence and ſelf-love, whereby to ſerve our own turns upon him. Oh! conſider of ſuch a curſed diſpoſition, and for time to come, the more God delivereth, let us be the more carefull to depend on him ſtill. I wonder, beloved, which of you, that having received any deliverance from a diſeaſe, by the hand of a wiſe Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſician, will be any whit the leſs regardfull of the Phyſician, becauſe he hath cured him, will he not the rather know him againſt another time, and keep correſpondence and acquaintance with him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he knows not how ſoon hee may have need of him? So when God hath delivered us, let us not a whit ſlack our dependance, nay, depend on him the more; now we have known and felt him by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, therefore we ſhould the more take notice of him and his faithfulneſs, and cleave unto him. It was an excellent concluſion which the Church made,<note place="margin">Pſal. 124.8.</note> 
               <hi>Pſal.</hi> 124.8. upon her miraculous delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance from wrathfully inraged enemies, by the evident hand of God, which when ſhe hath affectionately ſet forth in the body of the Pſalme with praiſes that were due unto God for it: <hi>(Bleſſed be the Lord, who hath not given us over for a prey unto their teeth)</hi> ſhee concludeth, <hi>that her help ſtandeth only in the name of the Lord,</hi> as inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mating a reſolution to depend upon no other help but his for the time to come; and what the Church did then, let the Church do now. The Church now hath been parallel to the Church then in
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:111756:23"/>dangers, the wrath of wicked men hath been kindled againſt us in our dayes, as it was againſt <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and they have deſired to ſwallow us up alive: And the Church now hath been parallel to the Church then in deliverances, and thoſe wrought as evidently by the hand of God as theirs, If it had not been the Lord who was on our ſide, now may <hi>England</hi> ſay as <hi>Iſrael, If it had not been the Lord who was on our ſide, when men roſe up againſt us, then they had ſwallowed us up;</hi> And why then ſhould not the Church now be alſo parallel to the Church then in duty? upon the like experience to take up the like reſolution, even to truſt in the name of the Lord: and ſay, Our help is and ſhall be in the name of the Lord; Thus ſhould we make uſe or former deliverances, and experiences to increaſe our truſt and dependancie upon the Lord; And as this is our duty, ſo would it be very pleaſing to the Lord, who otherwiſe will be diſpleaſed with us, as he was with his people <hi>Iſrael,</hi> in ſo much that hee takes up a great complaint againſt them,<note place="margin">Numb. 14.11.</note> 
               <hi>Numb.</hi> 14.11. that for all the won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders he had done among them, they did not believe; <hi>How long will this people provoke me? and how long will it be ere they believe mee, for all the ſignes which I have ſhewed among them?</hi> I liſt not to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare any more, but I know not whether God hath not equally ſhewed his power and love, and faithfulneſs towards us in ſignes and wonderfull works, even at this day; not to ſpeak of thoſe ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to be forgotten wonders, the <hi>Armado</hi> in 88. and the <hi>Powder-treaſon,</hi> what heaven-born diſcoveries have we lately ſeen, and had experience of in this kingdom? what dangers God hath preven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, what deliverances he hath brought to you in the City, to the Parliament, and to the whole kingdome? Oh, let it not be ſaid af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter all this, God cannot get us to believe in him, the more God deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereth, the more let us depend on him.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, let us up and be doing by our own indeavours, when God worketh for us, and labour to go on with him, when he deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereth and goeth before us;<note place="margin">2 Sam. 5.24, 25.</note> That was Gods charge to <hi>David</hi> when he was to go againſt the <hi>Philiſtims,</hi> 2 S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m. 5.24.25. <hi>When thou heareſt the ſound of a going in the tops of the Mulbury trees, then thou ſhalt b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtirre thy ſelf, for then ſhall the Lord go out before thee to ſmite the boſt of the</hi> Philiſtims; <hi>and</hi> David <hi>did ſo, as the Lord commanded him, and ſmote the</hi> Philiſtims; we can never more ſeaſonably con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute our indeavours, and beſtir our ſelves, then when God goeth out before us. We ſee how it crowned <hi>Davids</hi> undertakings with
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:111756:24"/>ſucceſſe; and <hi>Davids</hi> ſpirit elſewhere was raiſed and inlarged to more eminent enterpriſes when he found Gods hand going along with him,<note place="margin">Pſal. 60.6.10.</note> 
               <hi>Pſal.</hi> 60.6.10. When the Lord had given him victory over his enemies in the field, hee goes about to beat them out of their garriſon alſo: <hi>I will divide</hi> Shechem, <hi>and mete out the valley of</hi> Succoth: Gilead <hi>is mine, and</hi> Manaſſeh <hi>is mine,</hi> Ephraim <hi>alſo is the ſtrength of my head, &amp;c.</hi> not content with theſe, hee thinks of en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering their garriſon, <hi>Who will bring me into the ſtrong City, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We ſhould likewiſe be incouraged to lay out our ſelves freely now when the Almighty ſtands up, nay, when the Lord of hoſts is pleaſed to become the God of our armies, and to fight for us againſt our enemies: Oh! that we could now joyn hearts and hands, and ſtand up as one man in the common cauſe of the Church and State; Now, I ſay, that God hath diſplaied a banner for them that feare him, and for the truth; now that God hath given out a Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of deliverance for <hi>Jacob;</hi> now that deliverance begins to come, we might pull it home to us by our wreſtings with God in prayer, and by going out unto battell, to help the Lord againſt the mighty: when a Bell is riſing, one pull will do more to ſet it up then three pulls will when it is fallen.</p>
            <p>Thus may we happily improve the tender bowels which wee ſee God carries towards us in our miſeries, to a full deliverance, that he may give us reſt from all our enemies round about, and eſtabliſh truth and peace together, in the midſt of us, from generation to ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration, which is, and leads mee to open, <hi>the expected end</hi> which the Lord intends to give his Church, even the laſt branch of the Text, the matter and reſult of Gods thoughts toward his people in diſtreſs, <hi>to give you an expected end.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The matter or the reſult of his thoughts, are <hi>peace</hi> and <hi>an expected end</hi> of their long and tedious captivity; <hi>and though their hope deferred</hi> hath made <hi>them heart-ſick,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 13.12.</note> yet <hi>when he deſire</hi> ſhall <hi>come, it will be a tree of life.</hi> (You ſee) even the thing that they can wiſh or expect; ſo that their deſire and Gods thoughts agree in the event, onely they differ in the point of time; it is in Gods thoughts to give them what they deſire, but not when they deſire it. The words which our tranſlation renders <hi>an expected end,</hi> are disjunctively rendred by the moſt: <hi>finem &amp; expectationem,</hi> ſo ſome; <hi>finem &amp; ſpem,</hi> ſo others; <hi>finem &amp; patienti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m,</hi> ſo a third ſort of interpreters: I will not trouble you with the ſuperficiall deſcants of any that would ſeverally ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:111756:24"/>theſe words, as that <hi>end</hi> ſhould relate unto their captivitie, God promiſeth them an end of that, and <hi>expectation</hi> ſhould relate unto their return into their own land, God ſhould give them their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation in bringing them back into their own countrey again: the ſenſe and meaning of the words more ſolidly, is, that Gods pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> was to give them ſuch an end of their captivity, as that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they ſhould alſo receive the end of their hopes and expectations: the yoke of their bondage ſhould be taken off, and their eyes again behold dear <hi>Judea,</hi> and <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> which lay ſo neer their hearts, and all this in a time fore-appointed by Gods counſels, though far off, even threeſcore and ten yeers. The point hence is:</p>
            <q>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctr. </seg>
               </label> Gods counſels have foreſet a good end at laſt to the Churches calamities.</q>
            <p>Particular churches may be, like thoſe ſeven famous churches in the <hi>Revelation,</hi> now laid waſte and deſolate; and the Church generall (as ſhe is viſible) may be brought low, <hi>inter ſuſpiria &amp; la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chrymas,</hi> her calamities may be ſo deſtructive and laſting, that ſhe may ſeem to have loſt her viſibility for a time, as the Prophet <hi>Elijah</hi> complained, when he fled from <hi>Jezabels</hi> fury,<note place="margin">1 King. 19.10.</note> 1 <hi>King.</hi> 19.10. <hi>I, even I only am left, and they ſeek my life to take it away:</hi> and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as the Lord often threatens his own people, that hee will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy them, yet ſtill there is a remnant ſaved, to return to be as a ſeed for a flouriſhing poſterity, that after the Church have lyen for a while among the pots, ſullied and all becolled with perſecution, ſhe may be as beautifull <hi>as the wings of a Dove, that is covered with ſilver, and her feathers with yellow gold.</hi> God intended deliverance and free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom to <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſeed after four hundred yeers affliction,<note place="margin">Act. 7.6.7.</note> 
               <hi>Act.</hi> 7.6.7. and though he led <hi>Iſrael</hi> a crooked way through the wilderneſs, to humble them, yet was it ſtill with an intent <hi>to do</hi> his people <hi>good in the latter end, Deut.</hi> 8.16. So that as by the courſe of nature,<note place="margin">Deu. 8.16.</note> the trees and plants that in Winter are drie and ſapleſs, and ſeem to be little better then dead, yet at the Spring recover, grow green again, and bear fruit according to their kinde, as being appointed thereto by the God of nature: ſo the Church, though ſhee ſeem to be an out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſt in the Winter of affliction, and even ſwallowed up of miſery, never to be healed, ſo long, ſaith the Prophet, as <hi>untill the cities be waſted without inhabitant, and the houſes without man, and the land be utterly d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſolate, and the Lord have removed men farre aw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 6.11.12.13.</note> 
               <hi>and there be a great forſaking in the midst of the land</hi> (ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>Judea,</hi> and his own people) <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 6. verſ. 11, 12, 13.
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:111756:25"/>
               <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> vigor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Calvin.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>yet in it ſhall be a tenth, and it ſhall return, and ſhall be eaten: as a teyl tree, and as an Oake, whoſe ſubſtance is in them, when they caſt their leaves: ſo the holy ſeed ſhall be the ſubſtance thereof;</hi> God will not only reſerve a remnant in the Church which ſhall out-live the Winter-like troubles which befall her, but that remnant ſhall be as <hi>ſeed,</hi> which, though it lie under the earth, and die, ſhall revive and bear fruit; Gods promiſe unto them ſhall be as effectuall to reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver and ſettle them in a peaceable and deſired condition (which is, <hi>to gi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e them an expected end</hi>) as the Spring is, by her vigorous influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, to make ſeeds and plants after the dead time of the yeer to be flouriſhi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>g and fruitfull: And ſuch thoughts there are in the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty his heart, and ſuch promiſes to the Church in his Word.</p>
            <p>For hee hath made a covenant with his people which he will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>n.</hi> 1.</note> even in their afflictions, and whereby hee hath graciouſly tyed himſelf, that hee will not caſt them away, but recover them, how ſeverely ſoever hee deal with them for a time in puniſhing their ſins: Admit he ſhould (as here in the Text he did) caſt them ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of their own into their enemies land,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>v. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.44, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> yet then, <hi>Lev.</hi> 26.44, 45. <hi>When they he in the land of their enemies, I will not caſt them away, n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ither will I abhorre them, to deſtroy them utterly, and to break my cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant with them: for I am the Lord their God; but I will for their ſakes remember the c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>venant of their Anceſtors.</hi> This proviſo was expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly put in, when God renewed his Covenant unto <hi>David</hi> and his ſeed, that as hee would be carefull on the one hand to puniſh the ſins of his people, in caſe they did tranſgreſs; ſo on the other hand, he would continue his love to them, and be mindfull of his covenant, <hi>Pſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l.</hi> 89.32, 33. <hi>I will viſit their tranſgreſſion with the rod,</hi>
               <note place="margin">P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>2, 33, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>4.</note> 
               <hi>and their iniquity with ſtripes, nevertheleſs my loving kindneſs will I not utterly take from him, nor ſuffer my truth to fail, my coven<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt will I not break:</hi> His truth ſhould fail, and his covenant ſhould be broken, if his Churches calamities ſhould not be brought unto a good end at laſt; if her temporall afflictions ſhould be endleſs, or ſwallowed up in eternall miſery; but the people of God in former times have confeſſedly found his promiſe made good in this particular alſo, as we finde in the confeſſions of <hi>Nehemiah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h 9 31</note> Neh. 9.31. Having ſet forth how the Lord was driven by their ſins to puniſh his people, by giving them up into the hand of the people of the lands, hee ſhewes us, that hee did not continue their miſeries upon them. <hi>Nevertheleſs for thy great mercies ſake thou didst not ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:111756:25"/>conſume them, nor forſake them, for thou art a gracious and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull God.</hi> Yea, it concerns the Lord to make good this covenant viſibly before the world, that he may be juſtified, even in the ſight of men, concerning his faithfulneſſe to the Church in her de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, Gods mercie is the great attribute which is finally to be magnified and ſet up in his diſpenſations toward the Church, as his wrath is to be in his diſpenſations toward his enemies, which are called the <hi>Veſſels of Wrath,</hi> as his people are called <hi>Veſſels of Mercie.</hi> In all w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> diſpenſations he ſo carrieth intervenient occurrencies, that at length they ſhall ſerve to further the glorifying of that attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute mainly intended, whatſoever they may ſeem to doe in our ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions for the preſent: as<note n="*" place="margin">Parcendo malis ita ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus es ſecun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> &amp; non ſecundum nos, ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut miſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rtus es ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cundum n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> &amp; non ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cund<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Anſelm.</hi>
               </note> an Ancient ſpeakes of God ſparing the wicked though he ſeem to be mercifull to them in our ſenſe, he is not ſo to them in his own intentions therein. But that ſparing them, ſhall further glorifie his juſtice upon them at length. The like we may ſpeak of his afflicting of his beloved people, it ſhall turne in the end to the advancing of his mercie, as it did in <hi>David,</hi> by his 01 own confeſſion, <hi>It is good for me that I have been afflicted.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So then we may be confident upon this ground, that the end of the Churches troubles ſhall be ſuch, as mercie may rejoyce in, and be magnified by, and ſuch as we may mark for good as aſſuredly as the Prophet doth the end of the perfect and upright man,<note place="margin">Pſal. 37 37.</note> 
               <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37.37. <hi>Mark the perfect man, and behold the upright, for the end of that man is peace:</hi> His life may be troubleſome, but his death ſhall bee comfortable; as the Iſraelites through a crooked &amp; tedious wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, came to the promiſed land at laſt: <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaid of their journey, in that wilderneſſe, it was <hi>to try them.</hi> As the Gold-ſmith puts his metall into the Furnace, that it may come out the purer; ſo the Lord dealt with his Church therin, that he might bring her forth of trouble to his mind, &amp; ſet her according to her deſire at laſt; ſo ſaith the Prophet, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 60.10, 11, 12. <hi>Thou, O God, haſt proved us, thou haſt tried us as ſilver is tried: thou broughteſt us into the ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 60.10, 11, 12.</note> 
               <hi>thou laideſt affliction upon our loyns, thou cauſedſt men to ride over our heads, we went through fire and through water: but thou broughteſt us out into a wealthy place:</hi> where we have the Church raiſing up her apprehenſions of Gods preſent mercies to a highher pitch, by reflecting upon the dangers through which ſhe came to enjoy th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m; however ſhee was
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:111756:26"/>neere ſhipwrack, ſhe is now not onely as a ſhip in ſafe harbour, but as on ſhore in a pleaſant countrey.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Some ſpeciall benefits in which the Churches troubles ſhall end, &amp;c.</note>We ſee then in the generall, the Churches troubles ſhall end well, but what kinds of good may be expected or hoped for as the fruit of them, we have not ſeen; I ſhall therefore in the next place briefly point at ſome particular good ends which we may hope and expect God will bring his Church unto by her afflictions.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, the refining of the Church herſelfe, which was intimated before, by trying her as ſilver is tried, in the Pſalmiſt; while ſhe is in afflictions, ſhe is as metall in the furnace, which comes out ſevered from the droſſe at length: the frequent allegories of waſhing and purging in Scripture, to this purpoſe, I forbeare, we will only take notice of the Prophets expreſſion,<note place="margin">Mal. 3.17, 18.</note> 
               <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.17. <hi>And they ſhall bee mine in that day when I make up my Jewels, then ſhall yee diſc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rne be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the righteous and the wicked.</hi> The Lord had been working up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them as a Refiners fire, and Full<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rs ſope in the former part of the chapter, by afflicting his people he had been cutting and poliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his jewels, that he might render them Oriently beautifull, and at laſt he ſtrings them, and makes them up to preſerve them as his peculiar Treaſure, in his Cabinet, wherein he placeth nothi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>g but things of price: Reformation then of the Church, whereby the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſeed ſhall be the ſubſtance thereof,<note place="margin">Iſai. 6.12.</note> 
               <hi>Iſai.</hi> 6.12. is one great good may be expected as the end of the Churches miſeries and afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, the juſt puniſhment of the wicked, whereby the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs and power of God ſhall be much exalted, as they were upon <hi>Ph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>raoh;</hi> for which <hi>Moſes</hi> indited a God-exalting ſong, and God himſelf is pleaſed to hold out this, as an incouragement to his people, to be patient in their afflictions; that when God hath done his work upon his people by the <hi>Aſſyrian,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſai. 10.12.</note> he <hi>will puniſh him, Iſa.</hi> 10.12. Nay, he will deſtroy him, Verſe 25. <hi>Yet a very little while, and the indignation ſhall ceaſe, and mine anger in their deſtruction:</hi> for the incouragement of a reforming childe, the father will throw the rod wherewith he was corrected into the fire; and this ſhall be ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected an end of the Churches calamities, that the people of God ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll rejoyce to ſee the Lord ſo jealous for them, to avenge the innocent blood of his ſervants: ſo the Lord calls upon them, <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.43. <hi>Rejoyce,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 32.43.</note> 
               <hi>O yee nations, with his people, for he will avenge
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:111756:26"/>he blood of his ſervants, and will render vengeance to his adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and will be mercifull to his land and to his people:</hi> and ſo the Lords people ſhall, as is promiſed,<note place="margin">Act. 58.10, 11.</note> 
               <hi>Pſal.</hi> 58.10, 11. <hi>The righteous ſhall rejoyce when he ſeeth the vengeance; ſo that a man ſhall ſay, there is a God that judgeth the earth,</hi> they ſhall rejoyce, not in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of the creature, but in the execution of righteous judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, the Churches calamities ſhall end in the kingdome of Chriſt, after the ſhaking of all nations, the deſire of all nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ſhall come, ſaith the Prophet,<note place="margin">Hag. 2.7.</note> 
               <hi>Hag.</hi> 2.7. When Chriſt firſt came, it was as a refreſhing after t e diſtreſſes of Gods people: ſo alſo the oppreſſions of Antichriſt, and the ſtirs that ſhall be in the world thereby, ſhall end in Chriſts next coming, when he ſhall confu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e the man of ſin with the ſpirit of his mouth, and with the brightneſs of his coming ſhall deſt oy him. The tumults that are in the world, ſhall raiſe up Chriſt unto his throne, though it be contrary to the purpoſe of thoſe that ra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe them: The Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet obſervably points at t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is in <hi>Nebuchadnezzars</hi> Image,<note place="margin">Dan. 2.34, 35.</note> 
               <hi>Dan.</hi> 2. that when the ſword ſhall have carried the government from one Monarchie to another, the Kingdome of Chriſt (ſhadowed out by the ſtone out out without hands, which when it had ſmitt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n the Image, became a gre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t mountain, and filled the whole earth, <hi>Verſe</hi> 34, 35.) ſhall put an end to the quarrels that are among the kingdomes of the earth, by taking down them, and ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tting up his own, that ſo all the kingdoms of the earth may become the kingdoms of the Lords Chriſt. This, I ſay, is another ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall <hi>expected end</hi> of the Churches calamities, which will bring with it a fulneſs of all kindes of bleſſings deſireable; all hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full things ſhall be removed out of the Church,<note place="margin">Iſa. 11.9.</note> 
               <hi>Iſa.</hi> 11.9. <hi>They ſhall not hurt nor deſtroy in all my holy mountain:</hi> there ſhall be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo a confluence of all temporall mercies comprized in the word peace, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 32.17. <hi>The work of righteouſneſs ſhall be peace,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 32.17, 18.</note> 
               <hi>and the eff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ct of righteouſneſs, quietneſs and aſſurance for ever, and my people ſhall dwell in a peaceable habitation, and in ſure dwellings, and in quiet reſting places;</hi> and it is not unworthy our beſt obſervation, how gloriouſly the Church is ſet forth in this kingdom of Chriſt, as ſhee ſhall be when it is come,<note place="margin">Iſa. 60.</note> 
               <hi>Iſa.</hi> 60.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>1</label> Firſt, this truth may be a foundation of ſtrong conſolation and
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:111756:27"/>hope unto the people of God this day, when the ark or ſhip of the Church is even covered with waves, and when other foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations are caſt down, that <hi>Gods counſels have determined,</hi> and he paſſed his word that <hi>there ſhall be a good end at laſt of his Churches calamities;</hi> If Gods people be in bondage under affliction for the preſent,<note place="margin">Zach. 9.12.</note> yet they are <hi>priſoners of hope,</hi> Zach. 9.12. For the word is gone out of the mouth of the Lord, <hi>It ſhall be well with them that fear God, which fear before him,</hi> Eccleſ. 8.12. Or what if wee live not to ſee an end of theſe heavie troubles? may it not much ſtay our hearts, that we know it ſhall go well with Gods Church at length: If it was <hi>Eli's</hi> greater grief that the Ark of God was taken, then that his own ſonnes were ſlain (ſo that he could hear of their death, and live, but the newes of the Ark being taken kills him preſently, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 4.17, 18.) it would have been, doubtleſs, ſo great a comfort to him if it had been well with the Ark of God, that hee would have cheerful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly born the loſs of his children; wee ſhould likewiſe receive ſo much comfort in this good newes concerning the Church, that wee ſhould rejoyce in it, though wee ſhould never live to ſee it otherwiſe then by the eye of Faith, as <hi>Abraham</hi> ſaw Chriſts day and rejoyced.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>2</label> Secondly, it ſhould incourage us to contribute what help wee may to bring about this good end to the Churches cal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mities: Gods counſels are brought about in a way of providence, wee ſhould therefore indevour to ſerve providence to bring about the promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed deliverance of the Church. Thus did <hi>Daniel</hi> even in the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of our Text, when he underſtood that there was a time appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for the redemption of the Jewes out of their captivitie, he ſets himſelfe to do what in him lies to further it,<note place="margin">Dan. 9.23.</note> 
               <hi>Dan.</hi> 9.23. We ſhould alſo lay out our ſelves freely in the Churches cauſe, what way ſoever we may be improved, whether in our counſels, or in our eſtates,<note place="margin">What wee ſhould do to further this good end, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </note> or in our perſons, we cannot be laid out in a better cauſe, wherein God himſelfe will be (nay is) ingaged for the event. For the furtherance of it,</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, we ſhould be carefull to remove any thing that might hinder this expected end from being accompliſhed: our ſinnes at home will hinder our Armies in the Field: Therefore <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> commanded the people of Iſrael to take heed of every wicked
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:111756:27"/>thing when the Hoſt went forth to battell,<note place="margin">Deut. 23.9.</note> 
               <hi>Deut.</hi> 23.9. Let not the luſt of thy pride lie in the way of our publicke deliverance, to make thee contend for a degree of Honour, while the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome lies a bleeding: Let not thy luſt of covetouſneſſe carry on a private deſigne of gathering by the ruines of the State: Let not thy luſt of envie or revenge lead thee to hazard the Kingdome for thy will upon thine adverſary, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, we ſhould labour after perſonall and domeſticall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, upon that ſpeciall duty the Lord promiſeth to heale a Land, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 7.14. This is that which will procure us peace,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 7.14.</note> not meritoriouſly, but conditionally, and by way of covenant,<note place="margin">Iſa. 32.17, 18</note> 
               <hi>Iſai.</hi> 32.17, 18. we find uſually that Righteouſneſſe is the mother of all comfortable and happy Peace.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, we ſhould pray for it, as <hi>Daniel</hi> did above mentioned, and as the Lord himſelfe preſcribeth in the very next verſe to the text, and promiſeth alſo it ſhall take effect. The Lord inable us to do our dutie, and of his own free grace performe his promiſe of delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Church, and accompliſh the thoughts of his heart toward her in due time. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="erratum">
            <p>Reader be pleaſed to read <hi>Babylon</hi> for <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> page 2. line 2.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
